<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The art of riding set foorth in a breefe treatise, with a due interpretation of certeine places alledged out of Xenophon, and Gryson, verie expert and excellent horssemen: wherein also the true vse of the hand by the said Grysons rules and precepts is speciallie touched: and how the author of this present worke hath put the same in practise, also what profit men maie reape thereby: without the knowledge whereof, all the residue of the order of riding is but vaine. Lastlie, is added a short discourse of the chaine or cauezzan, the trench, and the martingale: written by a gentleman of great skill and long experience in the said art.</title>
            <author>Astley, John, d. 1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836123</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 193:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The art of riding set foorth in a breefe treatise, with a due interpretation of certeine places alledged out of Xenophon, and Gryson, verie expert and excellent horssemen: wherein also the true vse of the hand by the said Grysons rules and precepts is speciallie touched: and how the author of this present worke hath put the same in practise, also what profit men maie reape thereby: without the knowledge whereof, all the residue of the order of riding is but vaine. Lastlie, is added a short discourse of the chaine or cauezzan, the trench, and the martingale: written by a gentleman of great skill and long experience in the said art.</title>
                  <author>Astley, John, d. 1595.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Denham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Astley, who is named on page A4r.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discourse of horssemanship.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Horsemanship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Art of Riding, ſet foorth in a breefe treatiſe, with a due interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of certeine places alledged out of <hi>Xenophon,</hi> and <hi>Gryſon,</hi> verie expert and excellent Horſſemen:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein alſo the true vſe of the hand by the ſaid</hi> Gryſons rules and precepts is ſpeciallie touched: <hi>and how the Author of this preſent worke hath</hi> put the ſame in practiſe, alſo what profit men <hi>maie reape thereby: without the knowledge</hi> whereof, all the reſidue of the order <hi>of Riding is but vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtlie, is added a ſhort diſcourſe of the Chaine <hi>or Cauezzan, the Trench, and the</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale: written by a Gentleman of <hi>great skill and long experience in</hi> the ſaid Art.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jmprinted at London, by</hi> Henrie Denham. 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:375:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:375:2"/>
            <head>To the Right worſhipfull <hi>Gentlemen Penſioners, M. Henrie</hi> Mackwilliam, and M. William <hi>Fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ams.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ'd the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull M. Alley M. of the lewell houſe, earneſtlie to deſire me to ſatisfle you right worthie Gentlemen his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good freends, as touching the right vſe of the <hi>Canezzan</hi> firſt mooued vnto him by you Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Mackwilliam, as afterward for the like vſe alſo of the Bit, by you M. Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>williams, and that in writing; the which things both doo ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie reſt in the true vſe of the hand, wherein the chiefe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the whole Art of Riding ſtandeth: I was in great doubt what anſwere to make. For as I was verie loath to denie the earneſt requeſt of ſuch a perſon, to whom I thought my ſelf ſo greatlie bound; ſo doo I feare to fall into the iuſt blame that they deſerue, which take vpon them the thing that is aboue their power, or ſo preſume to put themſelues in preaſe among ſo manie, as haue ſo well written of the ſaid Art alreadie.</p>
            <p>But herevnto, he (as one more deſirous to ſatisfie you, than willing to vnburden me) anſwered and ſaid; Though it be true in deede, that diuerſe haue ſo doone, yet euerie one that is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be a profeſſor, or at leaſt a practiſer of this Art (as the whole companie of valorous yoong Gentlemen ought to be)
<pb facs="tcp:375:3"/>doo not conceiue the true meaning of the ſaid Authors rules, or can iudge of the errors of ill teachers, by whom they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued otherwhiles rather than taught, as by the dailie practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them one may eaſilie perceiue.</p>
            <p>The true vſe of the which are not gotten at the firſt aſſaie, but by long experience, and dailie conference with ſuch as haue had long practiſe in the ſaid Art, as he ſuppoſeth I haue had: and here vpon makes me beleeue I may doo ſomewhat to the great profit of ſuch yong beginners, though not by giuing of new, or altering the old, but by the way of interpreting, expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or ſhewing the reaſons of ſuch rules, as ſpeciallie in this point, which is cheeflie purpoſed to be treated of at this time, that is, concerning the true vſe of the hand: a thing not eaſie, but very hard to be vnderſtood, and feweſt rules be giuen ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and commonlie moſt vnſkilfullie vſed: ſo as thereby they maie the better vnderſtand the meanings of thoſe Authors, &amp; alſo iudge of others doings, and be more warie in their owne practiſings. And by this meanes alſo he perſuadeth me that I ſhall auoid the dangers which I before ſo greatlie doubted of, and thus hath he coniured me (as it were) to take this matter vpon me, as he ſaieth you haue doone him M. Mackwilliam verie oftentimes to haue it doone.</p>
            <p>In this maner therefore thus moued therevnto, I ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to doo my beſt to ſatisfie you all, yet letting you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand therwith, that as the ſhame is like to fall on me, if through mine vnablenes anie fault be iuſtlie found; ſo will the blame be common to vs all, but moſt to him, that hath been the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt procurer thereof; and leaſt to me (I hope) that was ſo loath to take this enterpriſe vpon me. Now then I haue firſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in what order I ſhall proceed therein. For how ſhall one make another vnderſtand, to what purpoſe the pomell of a ſword ſerueth, if he ſhew him not firſt what a ſword it ſelfe is? euen ſo how ſhal a man make another know what the true vſe of the hand is in the Art of Riding, if firſt he dooth him not to vnderſtand in generall, what the verie Art it ſelfe in nature is?</p>
            <p>I therefore haue thought good to proceed in this maner.
<pb facs="tcp:375:3"/>Firſt, to ſhew what this Art is, and out of that to draw the right vſe of the hand. The firſt part I will paſſe ouer with a ſhort diſcourſe, and confirme the ſame with approued authorities. The other, as touching the true vſe of the hand, I meane to ſhew, by telling in what ſort I haue practiſed thoſe Authors rules, and what profit I haue found thereby; and therein by the waie to interpret and explane where neede ſhall ſo require, ſuch places as maie ſeeme in them anie thing hard or vneaſie to be vnderſtood.</p>
            <p>And ſo I will leaue it to your conſiderations, &amp; require you both moſt earneſtlie, before you make it common, that you will cauſe it to be peruſed priuatlie, by ſome particular freends skilfull in that Art, according to your promiſe M. Mackwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam, when you firſt motioned the matter vnto the M. of the Iewell houſe, as he hath often told me: among the which I wold moſt gladlie, that M. Th. Blundeuile ſpeciallie ſhould haue a vew thereof, who hath alreadie gathered verie diligentlie the whole ſubſtance of that booke of the order of Riding, which was written by that excellent M. in that Art Frederike Gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a noble Gentleman of the citie of Naples, and hath verie skilfullie put it in ſuch order, as if men take good heed, &amp; wilbe diligent, they cannot but greatlie profit thereby, to the great benefit of themſelues, and the ſeruice of their countrie. For the which, and manie other his good abilities, if this time were not too much vnkind and forgetfull, he could not lie thus hidden as he dooth.</p>
            <p>And this doone, then my requeſt is, that it maie be returned to me againe, before you proceed anie further: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon I will not faile foorthwith to ſend it you againe. And thus I leaue it to your fauorable interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and to your wiſe and freendly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, wiſhing you both that you moſt defire. The laſt of September, 1583.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By yours to command, G. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:375:4"/>
            <head>To our verie louing Companions, <hi>and fellowes in Armes, hir Maiesties</hi> Gentlemen Penſioners: and to the <hi>gentle Reader whoſoeuer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene practiſed by many excellent men in ſundrie profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to forbeare the publishing of their owne names with ſuch workes, as they haue ſet foorth with ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar skill for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Their intent wherein (as we conceiue) hath beene onelie this, to profit and benefit others, without regarding anie waie to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe praiſe or commendation vnto themſelues. VVhich franke and liberall kind of dealing, as it proceedeth (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les) of a noble diſpoſition of mind, which ſeeketh rather to doo, than to be ſeene in doing, and paſſeth not for ſo meane a reward, as is commonlie due for ſpeach, or for a mans tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell by his pen: ſo were it a kinde of iniurie, to ſuffer the names of ſuch excellent perſons (worthie to beare name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad aboue others) to rest in that ſort drowned in ſilence and darknes, and not rather to indeuor (though contrarie to their likings in that behalfe) to aduance their doings, and to make them openlie knowne vnto the world, thereby to receiue part of that honor which is due vnto them. For
<pb facs="tcp:375:4"/>praiſe and renowne is vnto none ſo iustlie due, as vnto thoſe, which in anie vertuous action doo least affect it. In this number, which is but rare, must we note vnto you (though perchance not without ſome offenſe vnto him) the worthie Gentleman M. Iohn Aſtley, maister of hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Iewell houſe, and Gentleman of hir priuie chamber, a man, beſides his reputation and countenance in Court, knowne to be of ſingular shill in the Art of Riding: who (in truth) being the Author of this treatiſe, and yet either for modesties ſake, or otherwiſe careleſſe, that the world should yeeld praiſe and commendation vnto him for his trauell therein taken, hath ſought by all the meanes he could (as maie appeare by the Epistle, vnder the Cipher of two letters herevnto prefixed) to ſuppreſſe, and in no wiſe to haue his owne name ſeene in the ſame; rather conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that anie other should carrie the opinion thereof, than he himſelfe: where as (by his fauor be it ſpoken) he ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue doone the contrarie, and to haue entituled his name vnto his owne worke, whereby the ſame should haue receiued both credit and reputation. Howbeit, this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being handled with ſuch exquiſite skill and iudgement, as by the peruſing of this booke you shall perceiue it is, it was an eaſie matter, thereby to haue knowen M. Aſtley, though his name had beene neuer ſo much diſſembled, or the ſame not otherwiſe notified vnto you: for the matter it ſelfe (no doubt) would ſoone haue lead you to iudge that to be his, which (happilie) few men els could haue doone but he. Therefore (for our partes) being loath that ſo worthie a Gentleman, who hath trauelled ſo carefullie, and ſo kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for the good of his countrie, and was the onelie-man, that perſuaded Maiſter Blundeuill to take first in hand his
<pb facs="tcp:375:5"/>worke of Frederike Gryſon (which we all haue receiued no ſmall benefit by) should be defrauded of his due commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though he himſelfe doo litle regard it. And becauſe the worke it ſelfe is ſuch, as may boldlie abide the cenſure of the most preciſe and skilfull in this profeſsion, and withall beſeeme his owne name verie well: we haue aduentured (as you ſee) not fearing anie blame for our boldnes herein, (becauſe in ſo dooing, we meane nothing but all loue and honor vnto him) to declare thus much vnto you, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the verie Author of this preſent worke, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth now of his friendlie liberalitie into your hands, to the end you maie reape both profit and pleaſure thereof, for both are verie largelie comprized in it. Vſe it, we praie you, with like kindneſſe as it is offered vnto you, and take benefit of it without cauill, or ouer-curious reprehenſion; wherein as you shall doo the Author himſelfe but iustice, and alſo make vs his faithfull true friends much behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſo shall you happilie encourage him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, to endeuor himſelfe againe to your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and greater benefit hereafter. From the Court, at VVhite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, the last of March. 1584.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>H. Mackwilliam.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>W. Fitzwilliams.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:375:5"/>
            <head>The Art of riding defined, with notes <hi>of courage in a Horſſe, the vſing and</hi> abuſing of an Horſſe, and what is iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>called the hardneſſe of a Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> mouth, &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">Cap. 1.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othing is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned more proper to mans nature, than the deſire to know a truth, nor any thing counted more foule, or groſſe, than to erre &amp; be deceiued. Seeing then that the thing purpoſed is for the knowledge of the true vſe of the hand in this Art of Riding and Horſemanſhip, which belongeth to the warre and feates of armes; and that in reaſon, the ſubſtance of a part of any thing cannot well be vnderſtood without the knowledge of the verie nature of the thing it ſelfe whereof it is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:375:6"/>part (as the vſe of the hand is but a part of the Art of Riding) I haue thought good ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Firſt, to ſeeke out what the verie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Art it ſelfe is, that thereby wee may the better vnderſtand this part whereof we purpoſe to treate. And thus not meaning to hold you long, I will ſaie foorthwith mine opinion thereof, the rather to ſaue the band, whereby I ſtand ſo farre indebted vnto you all, than that I thinke my ſelfe able to ſatisfie your skilfull expectations, and ſo vnder the correction of diuerſe Noble and many other Gentlemen befides your ſelfe, with a great number of others that at this daie are growne to ſome excellencie in this kind of Horſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip,
<note place="margin">The defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> I ſaie (for my part) that the ſaid kinde of Riding is an Art to make an horſſe, for the ſeruice aforeſaid, obedient to his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. In this ſhort kind of ſpeech (as I take it) the verie whole ſubſtance of the ſaid Art is fullie conteined, and therefore the words thereof are diligentlie to be weighed, but eſpeciallie theſe here following:
<note place="margin">The parts of the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition which ſtand vpon the eſſentiall cauſes.</note> as ART, an HORSE, a RIDER, and OBEDIENCE: which I meane for the better explaning of my conceipt, to paſſe ouer with a ſhort diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>ART therefore is an obſeruation of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:375:6"/>experiences tried &amp; gathered togither,
<note place="margin">The art is the cauſe efficient.</note> to be put in order, and taught to ſome good end. Three things are chieflie to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Art, that is: eaſines, readines, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectnes. Art alſo is ſaid to imitate nature.</p>
            <p>An HORSE is the matter and ſubiect wherevpon this Art worketh,
<note place="margin">The mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall cauſe.</note> and is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſenſible, and therefore ſo farre as he is mooued to doo anie thing, he is thervnto moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by ſenſe and feeling. Further, this is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all ſenſible creatures, to ſhunne all ſuch things as annoy them, and to like all ſuch things as doo delight them.</p>
            <p>The inſtrument wherby this Art is wrought,
<note place="margin">The cauſe formall is the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</note> is the RIDER, a creature reaſonable, and therefore ought to be able to render a reaſon of euerie thing that he teacheth, in making the horſſe obedient to his will, the which if he cannot doo, hee is to be ſuſpected as one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull of the Art, and knoweth not what hee dooth.</p>
            <p>OBEDIENCE,
<note place="margin">The cauſe finall is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</note> is a readie willingnes to doo the will of him that dooth command. But now by the waie, though euerie Rider be a creature reaſonable, yet euerie reaſonable creature is not a Rider, but he which only is skilfull in that Art.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:375:7"/>
            <p> Finally, the patterne that Art ſhould imitate, that excellent Philoſopher and valiant cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine XENOPHON in his booke <hi>De re equeſtri</hi> doth verie gallantlie ſet forth in theſe words: Note when you ſee a Horſſe (ſaith he) make haſte to meet with other horſſes,
<note place="margin">Notes of courage in a horſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion of what ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.</note> that be in his view, or mares rather, and then ſhall you ſee how nature mooueth him to ſhew himſelfe in his beſt forme and luſtines of courage, yea, both terrible and beautiful to behold: for then he will ſet vp his creſt, bow in his head, pricke vp his eares, gather vp his legs high and nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſwell in his noſtrils, and ſtart out his taile, &amp;c. This is now the patterne that the curious painter with all his skill dooth diligentlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor to imitate, but how much more ſhould the skilfull Rider doo the ſame?</p>
            <p>Of theſe horſſes thus to be made, as XENO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHON alſo writeth, there be twoo kinds: the one, for the ſeruice aforeſaid, the other for pompe and triumph, the which we call ſtirring horſſes, the vſe of which are verie profitable for this ſeruice, bicauſe they teach a man to ſit ſurelie, comelie, and ſtronglie in his ſeate, which is no ſmall helpe to him that muſt fight and ſerue on horſſebacke: but of this laſt I meane not now to ſpeake.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:375:7"/>
            <p> Of ſeruice in the warre or field on horſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, there be two kinds: the one in troops and companies, and thoſe be likewiſe of two ſortes, either in the maine battell, or skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh: the other, when men being ſingled by chance or of ſet purpoſe, meete &amp; fight hand to hand, which is moſt proper to this Art. Here you ſee now in this ſhort diſcourſe, how na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ordered this matter. Firſt, that Art muſt imitate hir: next, that the horſſe in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt be mainteined in luſtines of courage, and freſhnes of feeling, which is proper to him by nature: finally the Rider to make him obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient by reaſonable meanes, which by nature is proper vnto men: ſo as theſe twoo ſeuerall bodies may ſeeme in all their actions and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be as it were but one onlie bodie. Thus if nature be obeied, and hir order pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſelie kept, it cannot be but the end will haue ſuch ſucceſſe as we doo deſire.</p>
            <p>Contrarie to theſe things herein thus ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie paſſed ouer, as namelie Nature, Art,
<note place="margin">The three contraries to nature, Art, &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</note> and Reaſon: is violence, which nature abhorreth; error, which Art reiecteth; vnrulie paſſion of mind, which reaſon alwaies withſtandeth: and as they be contrarie in nature, ſo be they alſo in working, and therefore muſt needs bring
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:375:8"/>foorth contrarie effects, as we may ſee by thoſe horſſes, that both without courage and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines are ridden, with rawe noſes, bloudie mouthes and ſides, with their curbed places galled, turning their bodies one waie, &amp; their heads another waie, which things are brought to paſſe by the violent and vnskilfull vſe of the hand vpon the chaine, <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> muſroll, and ſuch like, which were firſt deuiſed to ſaue their mouths; and not to marre their noſes and muzzels.</p>
            <p>For where the true order of riding is not rightlie vnderſtood,
<note place="margin">Wherein the cheefe part of horſſeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</note> and the true vſe or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the hand (wherein the cheefe part of this Art conſiſteth) is vnknowne, or elſe by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermuch impatience baniſhed for the time, there the effects before rehearſed muſt needs follow. So that, when by thoſe violent meanes they be brought to ſuch paſſe, as they care nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for hand nor ſpurre, for bit nor <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> then are there new deuiſes of bits &amp; muſrolls, hard and ſharpe, for the amendment of theſe defaults, and ſo from one degree of violence vnto another. And yet when all is done, and that they find by proofe all their labour loſt, then they complaine of the horſſe, that he han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth on the hand and craueth the ſpurre, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:375:8"/>though it were the horſſes fault by nature, and not the riders ignorance by violence: which by thoſe meanes hath ſo dulled and deaded the ſenſes and feeling, as he feeleth little of paine, of pleaſure nothing at all, and of a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible creature is made a ſenſles blocke.</p>
            <p>Let not men be deceiued (as for the moſt part they be) in taking one thing for an other,
<note place="margin">A paralo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyſme to make that the cauſe of a thing which is not the cauſe.</note> and that to be the cauſe of a thing, which is not the cauſe. As ſome take wine to be the cauſe of drunkennes, whereas (in deede) it is the vntemperate deſire of the drinker, &amp; not the wine: and ſo is it the vntemperate hand of the rider, who gouerneth with the raines the bit in the horſes mouth, that breedeth the dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and hardnes (as it is commonlie called) and not the bit or the mouth of the horſſe. For (I praie you) tell mee in reaſon, is not yron harder than the mouth of any horſſe in the world? I graunt that there ſhould be certaine forms of bits deuiſed for the remedie or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of certain faults that may chance in a horſſes mouth.
<note place="margin">The vſe and abuſe of certaine bits for ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> But if they be deuiſed for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall correction, then be they violent, and the horſſe will neuer take pleaſure in them. But if they be made to remedie a default, or to eaſe anie griefe, then is there Art &amp; Reaſon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:375:9"/>vſed, &amp; the effect of pleaſure will follow ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But to conclude, to what end ſoeuer they be deuiſed, the hand muſt guide them, which if it want the due meaſure in preſſing or ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then will follow ſome euill effect, as in too ſlacke bearing, the caſting vp &amp; downe of the head, and the vnſtaiednes therof, and in ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, the thruſting out of the toong, with gaping and wrieng of his neather iaw,
<note place="margin">What is iuſtlie cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the hardnes of the mouth.</note> &amp; bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of hardnes in the gummes, whereby ſuch hard knobs doo grow, as commonlie are in the innerſide of labouring mens hands, which in deede may iuſtlie be called the hardnes of the mouth. But as theſe things happen by vnskilfull riders, and violent meanes by them vſed, ſo they ſeeke to remedie their owne defaults by more violent waies (as is before mentioned) vntill they aſcend vnto the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of violence moſt horrible to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as by cutting thoſe knobbes, and their toongs out of their mouthes, and alſo the griſſels out of their noſtrils, and thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the name of Butchers rather than of Riders.</p>
            <p>Nowe that I haue in this ſhort diſcourſe comprehended the whole ſubſtance of the Art in generall, there is next to be ſhewed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:375:9"/>how an horſſe may be brought to this perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction before mentioned by the true vſe of the hand, ſo farre as the Art in that point will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer or allow: and further to require were more of curioſitie than of skill. For euen the beſt Phyſicians doo not alwaies heale the patient that is vnder their cure: neither is euerie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of one diſpoſition, nor euerie ſcholer of like aptnes to learne.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>A confirmation by other authors <hi>of this that hath alreadie</hi> beene ſet downe.</head>
            <head type="sub">Cap. 2.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt yet before we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into this part, let vs ſee (as we haue purpoſed) what thoſe excellent authors that write of this Art haue ſaid thereof. And for the auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of tediouſnes, ſeeing they all agree in ſubſtance, not excluding anie, yet make ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall choiſe of ſome, which I (for my part) would wiſh ſhould not exceede the number of twoo, whereof the one ſhould be <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:375:10"/>which wrote thereof in ancient time about 300. yeares before the comming of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and the other <hi>Gryſon,</hi> which of late daies hath done the like.
<note place="margin">Xenophon a great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher &amp; an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r Captaine.</note> And that the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe this <hi>Xenophon</hi> was not onelie a great Philoſopher, but alſo an excellent Captaine, ſpeciallie ouer the horſſemen, as it ſhould appeare: ſo as no exception can be taken againſt ſuch a one, as either for want of learning or experience may be obiected, which commonlike there is at this day if anie want either of them. And what that worthie Gentleman <hi>Frederike Gryſon</hi> was, euerie one knoweth, of nation an Italian (which nation hath long borne, and doth beare at this daie the onelie praiſe of this noble exerciſe) and of the citie of <hi>Naples</hi> moſt famous of all other in <hi>Jtalie</hi> in this reſpect. What his iudgement was in the ſaid Art, may appeare to all them that liſt to looke vpon the rules and precepts ſo perfectly ſet foorth by him in writing. What his practiſe was in the ſaid Art open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and dailie in the ſaid citie, and what his praiſe was there amongſt the reſt of excellent Riders, yea euen at that time when this Art was in his higheſt perfection, doth appeare in that noble <hi>Carociolos</hi> writings, the Duke of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:375:10"/>
               <hi>Martinas</hi> brother, which he intituleth <hi>Gloria de caualli,</hi> whereof he wrote ten books, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he reckoneth vp wel-neere a hundred as well Princes as Noblemen and Gentlemen: among the which Noblemen of that citie, that were deſcended of the Senators, thus he writeth of <hi>Gryſon,</hi> and of one <hi>Giovanni Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rardino de la Castella,</hi> in the latter end of the ſecond of his ſaid bookes, <hi>Tracoſtoro fioriſcono,</hi> &amp;c. which may be engliſhed thus:
<note place="margin">Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of excellent horſſemen.</note> Amongſt theſe floriſhed <hi>Frederike Gryſon,</hi> and <hi>Giovan Berardino de la Castella:</hi> of the which two in this noble exerciſe it may be ſaid as <hi>Petrarch</hi> ſaid of <hi>Tullie</hi> and <hi>Maro;</hi> Theſe be the eyes of our toong. For beſides the true knowledge of this Art, and the great practiſe they both had thereof, they with a moſt perfect iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had this ſpeciall grace giuen them, that euery horſſe at the firſt riding ſeemed to obey vnto them euen at their becke, ſo as the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by were aſtonied thereat: wherevpon all other ſtudious of this exerciſe would vnto theſe two perſons (as to the oracle of <hi>Apollo</hi>) verie often reſort, to be reſolued in all their doubts. Vpon theſe two therefore that haue written of that Art, that is <hi>Xenophon</hi> and <hi>Gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> I would wiſh all thoſe that are deſirous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:375:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:375:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:375:12"/>to haue the true order and exerciſe of this Art, ſpeciallie to ſtaie themſelues, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantlie to follow. Whoſe iudgements in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall (concerning the ſame) I mind to paſſe ouer ſhortlie, and after to touch particularlie the vſe of the hand.</p>
            <p>The gods (ſaith <hi>Xenophon</hi>) haue granted this vnto men,
<note place="margin">The means how to make an horſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the riders mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> that one of them may inſtruct and teach another by ſpeach; but no man can inſtruct and teach an horſſe by his ſpeech: but if you will cherriſh and make much of him, when he hath done well and to your liking; &amp; againe, puniſh him when he reſiſteth and will not be obedient to your will, he will ſoone and eaſilie learne to doo thoſe things which are required of him, according to your mind and liking. And this is ſpoken (ſaith he) in few words, but it ought diligentlie to be obſerued throughout the whole Art of Riding. For a horſſe will make the prouder auant and ſhew of his dooings, and better obey in all other things, when he hopeth to be made much of, and to haue reſt after he hath done and ended his trauell.
<note place="margin">The hart of a horſſe, &amp; the chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike humor in a man compared.</note> For (ſaith he againe) the hart of a horſſe is like to the humor of choler in a man: ſo then as men are not eaſilie prouoked or ſtirred to anger, vnto whom nothing is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:375:12"/>ſaid or done that may vex them; ſo a horſſe will not lightlie be mooued, vnto whom a man doth no harme or hurt.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is to be prouided, that the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der doo not trouble or vex the horſſe (for we muſt know that all ſudden things doo mooue perturbation in horſſes.) And further he ſaith, We ought to abſtaine altogither from thoſe things, which the moſt part of men doo vſe in opinion for the beſt kind of riding, that is, to force them on the hand with the bit, and to torment them with ſpurres, rod, or whip: for by thoſe meanes all things ſhall happen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to that which we deſire, that is, to haue him doo all his things in his beſt courage, ſhape, and forme, which will not be brought to paſſe by making him afraid with beating and ſpurring, driuing him into great pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations: for all ſuch things happen vnto thoſe horſſes, to whom the riding is greeuous and painefull, and that to their great ſhame and lacke, and not to their praiſe and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In another place he ſaith: that the beſt waie to teach (as it ſeemeth vnto me) is to obſerue &amp; hold that which I haue often here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore rehearſed, that is,
<note place="margin">The beſt way for a Rider to teach a horſſe.</note> that you remember to cheriſh your horſſe when he hath done wel.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:375:13"/>For whatſoeuer a horſſe doth by compulſion and force, he neither knoweth what he doth, nor how to doo it, neither will it become him, no more truelie than a Plaier that ſhould be driuen with whipping to plaie his part braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie on the ſtage. For aſwell the horſſe as the man deſerueth worthily diſpraiſe, rather than anie praiſe or commendation, when they be driuen therevnto by beating and ſtrokes.</p>
            <p>Therefore wee muſt with certaine quiet ſignes prouoke him to ſhew himſelfe luſtie &amp; comelie in euerie part aſmuch as he may: ſo as the profitableſt waie of teaching the Art of Riding is, not to deale rigorouſlie or haſtilie: for anger foreſeeth nothing, and is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of repentance.</p>
            <p>But if your horſſe haue beene vſed to haue been ridden quietlie with a ſoft &amp; gentle bit, &amp; hath by ſuch meanes learned all his leſſons, and other dooings, and can carie therewith his head and necke comely and decently, it ſhall be beſt that you trouble him with none other kind: for he will by this moſt eaſilie and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie doo and performe thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he him ſelfe is cheeflie delighted, and wherein he pleaſeth himſelfe moſt. And that he doth take pleaſure in thoſe things afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:375:13"/>let this be a good witneſſe and token thereof (ſaith he:)
<note place="margin">Xenophons proofe of the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> and therevpon he ſetteth downe that ſhape and forme that Art ſhould imitate, as is before mentioned, and then concludeth thus: that He therefore, who can by this meanes and order of riding, bring an horſſe in all his dooings and motions to ſhew this forme and ſhape which he himſelfe doth expreſſe and repreſent, when he would ſeeme and appeare moſt beautifull, ſhall bring to paſſe, that both the horſſe ſhall take great pleaſure of the riding, and alſo that he ſhall appeare to the beholders verie noble, terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and beautifull. Thus farre <hi>Xenophon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gryſon</hi> in the 9.
<note place="margin">Gryſons iudgement of the Art of riding.</note> page of his booke &amp; laſt edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſet forth Anno. 1571. vpon the margin of the which this note is ſet downe, <hi>Diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na de caualli,</hi> deliuereth his iudgement in generall of this Art, wherein (amongſt other things) he noteth: that Such are not mooued altogither without reaſon, which hold that a horſſe, being in Latine called <hi>Equus,</hi> tooke his name of the Latin word <hi>Aequu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or <hi>Aequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> which in Engliſh is Equall, or Iuſt. For thus he writeth: <hi>Et non in tutto fuor di ragione ſi mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouono coloro, che teng ono cheil Cauallo in lingua Latina prendeſſe il nome dalla equalita. ô guistez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za:</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:375:14"/>and ſo goeth on and ſaith, that He ought to be iuſt in paſe, iuſt in trot, in gallop, in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier, in ſtop, in mannage, in bounding, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie, iuſt of head, and iuſt when he ſtandeth ſtill, and to vnite himſelfe iuſt with the will of his Rider that ſitteth vpon him. And among al theſe things he commendeth the trot, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth, that thereby all the other qualities may be beſt brought to perfection, and the head and necke to great ſtaiednes, the mouth to a ſweete and perfect good ſtaie, the which (to end withall) he counteth to be the verie foundation of the whole Art: in the true tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching wherof if one faile, he marreth the horſſe vtterlie, and hideth all the goodnes that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath giuen him. Whereas on the other ſide, if he be truelie taught, it will ſupplie many parts wherein nature may faile him. And in the 59. page the 7. line beginning <hi>Et perche,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Diſorders vſed in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be auoided.</note> he writeth, that he is forced to note vnto vs that are deſirous to flie the diſorders that manie doo vſe, which by changing of hard &amp; ſharpe bits, thinke they ſhall ſtaie the head, or make the horſſe ſtoppe orderlie, and doo not ſee how thereby they make a iade of vile courage, or ouermuch exaſperate him: by the which greeuous error it ſhall neuer be poſſible
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:375:14"/>to bring him to anie good perfection, but by good Art and true diſcipline, and with a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant bit, wherevpon he may ſtaie his mouth temperatlie with ſafetie &amp; aſſurednes, by bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the hand temperate or firme vpon the trot or gallop, and in time to cherriſh him when he dooth well, and likewiſe to chaſtiſe him when he dooth ill, he will be fullie brought to all good, and conforme himſelfe to the will of his Rider.</p>
            <p>And in the 105. page,
<note place="margin">Ignorance the cauſe why none haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to write of the Art of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> where he treateth of theſe things more particularlie, he affirmeth in the end, that the ignorance of theſe things hath beene the cauſe, that none haue euer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to write of this Art, and that he is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that manie will blame this that he hath ſet downe, bicauſe it appeareth vnto them that this manner of teaching ſhould be falſe and vntrue, being verie ſtraunge and out of vſe, from all other which were and be now in the world. But all they which hereafter ſhall ſee what good effects doo grow by this order of teaching, ſhall know the great goodnes of the infinite grace that the heauen dooth now yeeld them. And in the verie laſt lines of his whole work he thus endeth, <hi>Queſta é quelto ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, la qual ſi ſegne da molti &amp;e tanta la difficolta,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:375:15"/>che vn ſolo ſara colui, che al fui compitamente ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuera al ſuo vero ſegno.</hi> Thus farre in generall I haue not onelie ſet downe mine owne, but haue alſo ſhewed the iudgement of theſe two authors to confirme the ſame, as I hope they doo, and as it will further appeare in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular rules and precepts, which they giue, in teaching how this iuſtnes and perfectnes may be brought to paſſe: wherein we ſee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie this to be receiued for a ſound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion and ground,
<note place="margin">A ſound principle or ground in the Art of riding.</note> that no forced or violent meanes are herein to be vſed: and alſo that this maner of riding is not vſuall, neither eaſie to be followed or found out, though it be ſet downe in writing neuer ſo plaine.</p>
            <p>For doo we not ſee that in al other arts there is a beginning, a proceeding, and laſt of all the perfecting?
<note place="margin">Familiar examples for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Authors purpoſe.</note> As for example, in the art of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, firſt, there is the learning of the letters, next the well ioining of them togither, and laſt, the continuall exerciſe thereof to bring the hand eaſilie and readilie to write perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, as faire and well as the perfect example that was firſt ſet downe. And doo we not ſee alſo, that if there be a thouſand Scholars, and all they haue but one example giuen them, and by one waie of one maiſter taught, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:375:15"/>when they haue vſed to follow the ſame and none other, ſo long as it may be thought time for them to leaue the ſchoole, and be able to teach others, that yet all they ſhall ſo differ in writing, as that their hands may eaſilie bee knowne one from the other, yea, and from the firſt example too. For markes are not ſet vp, bicauſe that good markemen can alwaies hit them (for that is not poſſible) but he is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the beſt Archer, that beateth continuallie neareſt about it, and dooth (for the moſt part) hit it more than anie other, and that is poſſible enough.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>The true vſe of the hand vpon the bit, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>the Cauezzan, ſet downe as it hath beene</hi> found true by experience: and alſo of a fault <hi>in ſaddles which hinder the riders hand in the</hi> directing of his horſſe.</head>
            <head type="sub">Cap. 3.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd now ſeeing I am light vpon this example,
<note place="margin">The true vſe of the hand vpon the bit, &amp;c.</note> which, in the cheefeſt point that belongeth therevnto, agreeth with the principall point of this exerciſe; that is, to the firme and ſtaied direction of the hand (of the which my
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:375:16"/>purpoſe is cheefelie to treate) my minde is now to conſider of the particular rules and meanes the which haue beene giuen by theſe Authors in that point, for the perfecting of this cauſe in hand, wherein the true vſe as well of the hand vpon the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> as vpon the bit, may be knowne, conſidering they be both vnder the gouernment of the hand.</p>
            <p>And heerein I meane to ſatisfie the ſpeciall requeſt of maiſter <hi>Mackwilliam,</hi> as touching the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> as farre as my abilitie will ſerue. But of the mind of theſe authors I cannot ſaie much thereto.
<note place="margin">Xenophon, though treating of the Art of riding, yet ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Cauez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan.</note> For in <hi>Xenophon</hi> I find nothing at all written thereof: and in <hi>Gryſon</hi> litle or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe, as in diuers places heere alledged out of him one may perceiue: as in the laſt line (ſaue one) of the ninth page be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore recited, he firſt maketh mention thereof, ſaieng; <hi>Come egli ander á ſicüro, et ſolo in Cauez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zana, ſenzache altro il tiri:</hi> and in the thirtenth page, whereas hee treateth of making the horſſe to ſtoppe iuſt: and alſo in the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, where he ſheweth what maner of bit he would haue the horſſe weare firſt: and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the ſixteenth, when hee would haue the <hi>Cauezzan</hi> taken from him: and againe in the 23. page the fourth line, wherein he warneth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:375:16"/>the rider when he mannageth the horſſe vpon the halfe time, to take heed that he wrie not his necke, but to helpe him skilfullie with the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uezzan:</hi> and ſo againe for the ſaid fault he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention thereof in the latter end of the 79. page: and laſt of all in the 82. treating ſtill of correction for the ſaid fault, he concludeth thus; <hi>Caualiero fondato in buona dottrina ſenza di ciolo togliera non ſolo di queſto ma d'ogn' altro vitio,</hi> that is: that the Rider grounded in the right order of teaching, without it ſhall take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way not onlie this fault from him, but euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatſoeuer.
<note place="margin">Who is beſt groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Art of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> And who is beſt grounded in this skill, he ſheweth in the 106. page, at the 33. line, begining thus, <hi>Et vi fo noto, &amp;c.</hi> I doo you to know, that euerie one which ſhall know how to correct, to aid, and to cherriſh a horſſe, according as it behooueth him in time, may be called the moſt grounded in this skill. And a little after he ſaith thus, <hi>Ma par arriuare a tal virtu &amp; in oqui ſua bonta, dico, &amp;c.</hi> But to come to ſuch goodnes and perfection, I ſaie (ſaith <hi>Gryſon</hi>) that euen as the ſhip is guided by the ſteeres man, by meane of a ſtearne; ſo a horſſe ſhould be gouerned, according as his ſtearne is mooued, which is the bridle, and the reines thereof, and that he termeth <hi>Il manico
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:375:17"/>del timone,</hi> the handle of the ſtearne, the which be holden in the left hand, and guided by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and diſcourſe, ſo as it behooueth that in all his motions and actions he anſwer to that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the hand mooueth that holdeth the bridle. Now ſeeing then the ground of all the Art (as he often affirmeth) reſteth wholie vpon the true vſe and iuſt gouernment of the hand, let vs of this moſt cheefe and neceſſarie point therefore ſee, what theſe authours ſaie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. For in treating hereof will appeare not onelie the true vſe of the hand vpon the bit, but alſo vpon the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> and the whole ſecret alſo of this Art to them that with reaſonable diſcourſe and heedfull diligence doo conſider thereof, and that doone, I (for my part) will ſhew the experience, with the profit that I haue found by practiſing of them.</p>
            <p>And yet of one thing by the waie,
<note place="margin">A fault in ſaddles hindering the right vſe of the hand in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> I muſt put you in remembrance, moſt contrarie to the right vſe of the hand, and therefore in no wiſe to be vſed, and that is your new deuiſed ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of late, that haue their pomels too much bending forward, with a buttreſſe (as it were) vnderneath it of an handfull thicke and more, ſo as no man can draw his hand toward him low vnder the pomell to ſtop or gouerne the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:375:17"/>horſſe, as <hi>Gryſon</hi> teacheth, <hi>Vicino al garreſe,</hi> that is, neere to the withers, but muſt of force keepe it forward, and when he ſhould ſtoppe his horſſe to heaue it vpward for to draw it to him, he cannot, vnleſſe he doo it aboue the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell, and in ſo dooing may chance to knocke his knuckles therevpon, except he keepe his hand verie much forward, which to doo at the ſtoppe is againſt all reaſon: and beſides, it is cauſe of manie diſgraces, as well to the rider, as to the horſſe himſelfe: the which to ſhew I meane not now to trouble you withall, and therefore to the matter purpoſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>The vſe of the hand vpon the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uezzan, more ſpeciallie touched; and how</hi> diuerſlie it is miſvſed for want of skill, a leſſon for yoong beginners in the Art of riding.</head>
            <head type="sub">Cap. 4.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow to ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The vſe of the hand vpon the Cauezzan, &amp;c.</note> thogh <hi>Gryſon</hi> for his own part ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to make no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereof, yet he alloweth that others ſhuld vſe it, when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:375:18"/>he maketh mention of the ſame in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (as I haue before remembred) and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth men to vſe it skilfullie, as in the 23. page the third line, there treating of the mannage with the half reſt, he vſeth theſe words; <hi>Adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndolo maeſtreuolmente conta Cauezzana,</hi> that is; To aid him skilfullie with the <hi>Cauezzan.</hi> So as it appeareth in theſe words, that there is a skill or cunning in the vſe thereof, leauing it euen ſo to the diſcretion of him that vſeth it, thinking peraduenture, that thoſe rules which he hath giuen for the vſe of the hand vpon the bit, might ſerue alſo for the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> to him that hath anie reaſonable diſcourſe. So as (in mine opinion) if we would but conſider the generall ground verie diligentlie, that is, that we doo not ſo preſſe the place whereon it lieth, with ouer hard a hand, as therby the ſenſe may be dulled, but ſo temperatelie vſed, as the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling may alwaies be freſh (the which I feare is ſmallie conſidered of manie that vſe it at this daie, as farre as I can ſee) we ſhould ſee better effect follow thereof, than we ſee oftentimes there dooth.</p>
            <p>I thinke therefore the beſt waie to make men to vnderſtand the true vſe of the ſame,
<note place="margin">How the Cauezzan by diuers is miſvſed.</note> is firſt to let them know, how by diuers it is miſv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:375:18"/>and that it is miſvſed, whatgreater proofe can there be more manifeſt, than to ſee how miſerablie the ſillie horſſes be tormented and mangled therewith about their noſes, ſo as the skinne and fleſh is worne to the bones: and where it ſhould lie flat by nature <hi>Come vn mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone</hi> (as <hi>Gryſon</hi> ſaith) like to the noſe of a ſheepe, they by their violence make it ariſe in the middeſtlike to the beake of a hawke. How doo we ſee their heads alſo ſet out of frame by reaſon of the miſuſe thereof, when the horſſe is taught to turne therewith: and (as <hi>Gryſon</hi> noteth) to their great ſcorne that ſo teach them, in the 82. page of his booke, whereas he ſpeaketh of ſome horſſe, that hath been taught from the beginning vnto the end, to turne with his noſe and necke awrie, ſaieng thus; <hi>Per colpa del' caualiero non vi fu mai prouisto, tal che egli ha fatto il ſuo lacerto inar cato da vna banda &amp; dalto altra fermo &amp; ſano, &amp; dimoſtrer à che vi ſia nato di quel garbo torto.</hi> And thus in engliſh: Through the fault of the rider not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing at anie time, how hee hath made his horſſe his Lacert bowed on the one ſide, and firme on the other,
<note place="margin">The nature of a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talie, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Lacerto.</hi>
               </note> as though he had beene foaled with that deformitie. This word <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certo</hi> is the name of a vermine or creeping
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:375:19"/>worme, like to a <hi>Newght,</hi> with foure feet, which in <hi>Jtalie</hi> be common, and haue this propertie by nature, neuer to looke directlie vpon a man but alwaies with his head awrie. And this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth (as he affirmeth) for lacke of taking heed of the vſe of the hand at the beginning, that guideth the <hi>Cauezzan.</hi> For euen as by violent haling thereof, they marre the naturall forme of their noſes, ſo by vnskilfull vſing of it, in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them the furrow turne (as ſome call it) they ſet their heads and neckes awrie, which is now commonlie ſeene. For if a horſſe be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on the one hand, you ſhall ſee him carie his head on the contrarie ſide.
<note place="margin">Of what error the fault in a horſſe of holding his necke and head awrie doth grow.</note> This vice grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of this error, that when the horſſe dooth not yeeld quicklie to the motion made with the reine of the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> to turne on that ſide his rider would haue him, then he pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it harder and harder, and therewith perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture his head yealdeth, but his bodie ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not at all. The Rider then perceiuing that diſorder, letteth that reine go, and bicauſe he ſhall not wrie his head in that ſort, he ſtaieth the reine on the contrarie ſide, ſo as his head cannot follow his bodie, and by this vſe and cuſtome of teaching, he is brought to the ſaid fault and vice aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:375:19"/>
            <p> But the true vſe of the hand in this point is,
<note place="margin">How to handle a horſſe in teaching him the furrow turne and how that turne is made.</note> that when the horſſe is brought to the place where he muſt be taught this furrow turne (that is in a new deepe ploughed ground, into a troden path, betweene two furrowes) and therein ſtandeth ſtrait and iuſt with his bodie (as <hi>Gryſon</hi> appointeth) mooue him gentlie to go forward, and in the verie motion turne him firſt on the right hand thus: Drawe the right reine faire and ſoftlie vnto you, taking the ſame with your right hand low vnder the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell of the ſaddle, well neare halfe a foote to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the middle of the reine, whervnto if he yeeld neuer ſo little, then make much of him, and ſtaie that hand with that reine, ſo as you neither draw it anie further, nor ſlacke it anie thing at all: and with your left hand let the left reine ſlacke, ſo farre as his head may turne, and haue libertie to go and follow his bodie, and no further.</p>
            <p>But if you perceaue with that little yeelding,
<note place="margin">What helps muſt be vſed in this kind of training.</note> his bodie mooueth not with his head, then helpe him gentlie with your left leg, but let not your hand ſtirre. If this will not ſerue, let his keeper, or ſome other that hath skill, be with you, that may faire and quietlie come on his left ſide to his foreſhoulder, and thruſt him
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:375:20"/>by little and little to cauſe him mooue the fore part of his bodie. But if the horſſes reſiſtance be much, let him vſe his force, and thruſt the horſſe from him as he ſeeth cauſe. Then in this meane time, let the rider alſo helpe him with the calfe of his leg (as is before mentioned) ſtriking him therewith as neere the ſhoulder as he may, and to make that ſound of the mouth or voice, that <hi>Xenophon</hi> ſpeaketh of, which hee calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and is made by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the tip of ones toong into the roofe of his mouth, and ſmartlie to looſe it by opening thereof. But in all this time he muſt keepe his hand firme and ſtaied, not ſlacking nor draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame by anie meanes. And aſſoone as he ſhall perceaue that the horſſe mooueth the forepart of his bodie (be it neuer ſo little) let him ſtaie and make much of him, but ſuffer him not to turne backe againe to the path, which peraduenture he will offer to doo, and in that manner bring his forepart about, vntill he come into the path againe, ſo that his head ſtand where his hinder part ſtood, and there ſetting all his foure feet right in the ſaid path, let him ſtand with his head and bodie, as ſtrait as you can deuiſe, and ſo let him reſt and make much of him, &amp; ſee that both the reines
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:375:20"/>be of equall length, and ſtand with him in that ſort a pretie while, and that doone, turne him on that hand ſtill, in ſuch order as before, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he be come about into the path, and that his head ſtand that waie therein, as it ſtood at the firſt when he began to turne: and alwaies when you offer him the turne, you muſt firſt put him forward, and in that verie motion, drawe the reine with your hand as before: thus as you haue doone with your right hand, ſo muſt you order your left hand alſo, when you turne him on the left ſide. Heere I haue touched diuers circumſtances, without the which I could not well ſhew that which is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie purpoſed, that was, the true vſe of the hand vpon the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> in teaching the horſſe to turne.</p>
            <p>But if you will haue a perfect view of the miſuſe of the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A perfect view of the miſuſe of the Cauez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan.</note> then marke when a horſſe is ridden with the bit and <hi>Cauezzan</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, and you ſhall ſee manifeſtlie, and that ſpeciallie when they be turned vpon the left hand, the miſuſe thereof. For then the rider, hauing both the reines of the bridle, and the left reine of the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> altogither in his left hand, thinking to helpe the horſve to turne on the left ſide, drawing all the reines
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:375:21"/>toward the ſaid ſide, with the which draught he draweth alſo the right reine of the bridle with the reſt, ſuppoſing thereby to helpe the horſſe, and dooth not perceiue how therewith the cheeke of the bit on the right ſide is ſo pulled vp, as thereby the mouth of the bit dooth ſo preſſe the horſſe on that ſide, that his head cannot follow his bodie towards the left ſide that he is offered to turne vpon, cleane contrarie to the order that he was taught, or ought to haue beene taught, when he was rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den onlie with the <hi>Cauezzan:</hi> for then hauing the right reine in the right hand, and the left reine in the left hand, they may be drawne on either ſide in reaſonable manner.</p>
            <p>But I doo not ſee how it is poſſible in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to teach a horſſe to turne on both hands, and keepe that forme and ſhape that nature hath giuen him, holding the reines of the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the reines of the <hi>Cauezzan</hi> in one hand.
<note place="margin">Leſſons for yoong beginners in this Art or exerciſe.</note> And therefore I would wiſh that yoong beginners ſhould not ride with the <hi>Cauezzan</hi> and bit togither, but rather with a watering bit made like to a ſnaffle, and hauing the mouth of a cannon bit, ſo as he might hold the reines of the ſame, one with the one hand, and the other with the other: as he dooth the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:375:21"/>reines of the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> whoſe iuſt and due place is to be borne low euen with the point of the ſhoulders, and not aboue the mane of the horſſe, as one muſt carrie them, if he will vſe them in one hand with the reines of the bridle.
<note place="margin">What muſt be doone in riding a horſſe with bit and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uezzan to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither.</note> But if they will needes ride with bit and <hi>Cauezzan</hi> togither, then to auoid the fault before remembred, I thinke this the beſt waie (in mine opinion.) Let them learne to change the reines of the bridle out of one hand into the other after this manner: when they turne the horſſe on the right ſide, let them drawe the right reine of the <hi>Cauezzan</hi> lowe to the point of his ſhoulder, with the ſaid hand as afore ſaid, &amp; then hold the reines of the bridle which you haue in the left hand with the reines of the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> right ouer the creſt and the necke of the horſſe, ſo as you preſſe his mouth nothing at all therewith. So likewiſe, when you turne him on the left ſide, change the reines of the bridle out of the left hand into the right, and then hold him with the right hand, euen as you did before with the left, and vſe the left reine with your left hand, as you did alſo with your right. Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing you by the waie, that in any wiſe in all your horſſes leſſons whatſoeuer, you ſhunne
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:375:22"/>making of ouermuch haſte with him, for that is as great an error and ouerſight as a rider may commit, and dooth as much hinder your horſſes profiting in that you would teach him as anie one thing. So muſt you be likewiſe heedfull to giue your horſſe breath in all his dooings. And thus much for the <hi>Gauezzan.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>The vſe of the hand vpon the bit <hi>more ſpeciallie declared; with diuers</hi> circumſtances incident to this <hi>diſcourſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Cap. 5.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow to begin with <hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The vſe of the hand vpon the bit, &amp;c.</note> as touching the right vſe of the hand vpon the bit, after he hath ſpoken of diuers kinds of bits wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he would haue horſſes ridden, he endeth thus: What kind of bit ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be (ſaith he) with the ſame muſt he be made to performe all thoſe things that be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, to ſhew himſelfe comelie, and in ſuch ſort as we haue preſcribed. And therefore the horſſes mouth may not be ſo preſſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:375:22"/>that thereby he be put to deſpaire of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, neither ſo eaſie or ſoft that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne or deſpiſe it. Now then, after you haue ſomewhat preſſed him with the bridle, ſo as he carrieth his necke well, then muſt you by and by eaſe your bridle hand, and make much of him, aſſoone as he ſheweth himſelfe obedient vnto you. Further he ſaith, that when you ſhall perceiue, that the horſſe is delighted and hath a certeine pride in the raiſing vp of his neck, and that he is well pleaſed with the eaſing of the bridle, you muſt take heed leaſt anie thing at that preſent be offered him, which beſide may then vex and greeue him, as though you would driue him to a perpetuall paine. But then you muſt winne him with gentle and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous dealing, whereby he may hope for reſt and quietneſſe: for by that meanes he will be more readie and willing to doo whatſoeuer you will haue him.</p>
            <p>In another place he willeth,
<note place="margin">How to ſtaie a fierce and ſtubborne horſſe in riding.</note> that if you will ſtaie a fierce and ſtubborne horſſe, you may not pull him with the bridle vpon a ſudden, but quietlie and patientlie pull it in by little and little, whereby you may allure and intice him, and not compell him by force to ſtaie and ſtand ſtill. Laſt of all he ſheweth, that gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:375:23"/>
            <p>This place therefore is diligentlie to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and heedilie to be conſidered, and warilie to be practiſed. But hitherto yet in theſe things, there hath beene rather noted what ſhould be doone, than taught how they ſhould be doone. And therefore in the 44. page, he dooth not onelie treate of the matter againe, but teacheth alſo how it ſhould be doone, and ſaith;
<note place="margin">How to make an horſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> If you will know how to cauſe a horſſe not onelie to vnderſtand the bridle, or to make him go backe therevpon, but alſo that he may go in a due meaſure and temper with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bearing vpon the hand, <hi>tenerete quest ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> doo you keepe this order: Aſſoone as you haue ſtaied your horſſe, draw with a ſtaied hand the bridle temperatlie, as his reſiſtance, or he by defending his mouth ſhall require, not giuing him anie libertie at all, and with the rod ſtrike him vpon the bowing of his neck faire and gentlie, and ſo for a while prouoke him with the ſpurre from time to time, one while with the one, &amp; an other while with the other: but moſt on that ſide where he moſt wrieth his buttocke, to the end he may go iuſt, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other meanes, as in thoſe places you may ſee, vntill at leaſt he draw back one of his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feete, and dooing but ſo much, by and by take
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:375:23"/>heed that therewith you make much of him (as I haue often told you, ſaith <hi>Gryſon</hi>) and then ſtaie him quietlie a little while, and after aſſaie againe to do the like, drawing onlie the bridle. For the horſſe, by reaſon of the cheriſhing you gaue him, ſhall vnderſtand you, and will go backe both with the one and with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forelegge, and that verie light vpon the hand.
<note place="margin">How to make an horſſe go as farre as one would haue him.</note> Alſo when you ſhall offer him that ſigne to touch him with halfe the rod vpon the necke, you ſhall with a lowd voice ſaie, Backe: for he, aſſoone as afterward he ſhall heare that manner of voice, and feele that ſigne of the rod, or if you doo but draw a little the bridle, he will go as farre backe as one will haue him, and euer when he ſhall be out of the due and true ſtaie vpon the bridle, you ſhall ſtill make him to doo the like, that is, to go backe in forme aforeſaid. And to incourage all men to practiſe this rule, in the latter end thereof he writeth thus: <hi>Et non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i diſperate, ſe quando ſe gli inſegna queſto, faceſſe qual che diſordine, perche all vltimo tanto maggiormente ſi trouera in meno ſpatio di vn bora caſtigato, et vinto, et aſſai faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le;</hi> which is to ſaie in Engliſh: Doo you not deſpaire, though when you teach him this, he make ſome diſorder; for by ſo much the more
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:375:24"/>at the laſt, one ſhall find him in leſſe ſpace than an houre, chaſtiſed and wonne verie eaſilie. Theſe places thus recited, bicauſe they be the principall places that I can find, that is, for this purpoſe, to haue a horſſe to haue a perfect good mouth, by meane of the true vſe of the hand: I meane, for the better keeping of them in remembrance, breefelie to gather the whole effect of this that hath beene ſaid.</p>
            <p>Wherein firſt I would haue one note the compariſon of a bridle with the ſtearne of a ſhip,
<note place="margin">What things the author would haue noted tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the praemiſſes appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to this Art.</note> which is placed in the horſſes mouth, and faſtned to the reines that are holden in the left hand, and likened alſo to the handle of the ſtearne, which in his owne toong he calleth <hi>Il manico del timone:</hi> and muſt be guided by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and diſcourſe, and that all the horſſes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and actions muſt be made to anſwer therevnto. And then more particularlie <hi>Gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſaith, that we ſhould make him know the bit, with a temperate and firme hand, and that doone, to beare it vpon a ſweete ſtaie, which he calleth <hi>Dolce appoggio:</hi> for therevpon he will waxe verie light vpon the hand, and haue a ſweete mouth, champing the bit with great pleaſure, for that is the point wherein conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth (ſaith he) one of the greateſt matters, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:375:24"/>greateſt ſubſtance to ſtaie the head of the horſſe, and to ſettle it in his due place: and there in that manner, with all the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as is before mentioned, to mainteine him without giuing him anie libertie at all, as <hi>Gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſaith, though it ſeeme otherwiſe to <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon.</hi> And then, how he may be taught to be brought to this, he hath ſet downe the order verie excellentlie and plainelie.</p>
            <p>But heerein note (aboue all) how warilie he ſpeaketh of the reſtraint of libertie vpon the horſſes, yeelding to the hand.
<note place="margin">What is to be doone touching the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of libertie in an horſſe.</note> For there he putteth in a caue at (as it were) that the ſtaied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or reſtraint of libertie ſhould not be ſuch, as it ſhould exceed the due temperature of the hand: the true tokens of the which be; if the horſſe reine well; and beare his head iuſt, ſtaied, and light therevpon, and take pleaſure of the bit. Theſe properties muſt ioine ſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, as there may not want anie one of them to what action ſo euer the horſſe is put. For if there doo, then is there ſome imperfection, whereſoeuer it is. And therefore I ſaie with <hi>Gryſon</hi> againe and againe, that you may not thinke ſlightlie thereof, that heerein ſtandeth cheeflie the whole ſubſtance of the Art. But now, though he hath heere plainlie ſet downe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:375:25"/>how it may be obteined, yet in practiſing the ſame, I feare we ſhall be verie often to ſeeke. For it is not inough, as it ſeemeth by <hi>Gryſon,</hi> that when he dooth go backe vpon the hand lightlie, and ſettleth his head in his due place, and taketh pleaſure vpon his bit, vnleſſe hee doo the ſame alſo vpon euerie other act when he ſhall be put therevnto. For commonlie vpon the ſtoppe, or when they ſtand ſtill, they will be in good order: but if you mooue him forward, yea but vpon the pace, he will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps leaue plaieng with the bit, and beare ſomewhat vpon the hand, or thruſt out his head, and ſo likewiſe vpon the trot, and more vpon the gallop, but moſt of all vpon the maine carrire.
<note place="margin">A fault in riding, committed for want of knowledge how to mainteine and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the hand iuſt, firme, &amp;c.</note> For how manie ſhall you ſee, yea euen at theſe daies, that in paſſing of the carrire holdeth his head in, and keepeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in that forme that is before appointed? And this commeth for want of the knowledge how to mainteine and continue the hand iuſt and firme, with a ſweete ſtaie vpon the horſſe (as is before remembred) in all his actions whatſoeuer, ſo as he may take pleaſure of the bit. And therefore, how we ſhall mainteine an horſſe, being once brought to know the hand, and in this ſort before mentioned, that he in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:375:25"/>all his dooings, whether they be doone furiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie or quietlie, may keepe himſelfe in his due forme and comelines, and to take pleaſure therein, is now to be conſidered, and laſt of all of <hi>Gryſon</hi> required, and hath ſet downe his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion thereof (as you haue read.) And for my part, although I may be as farre to ſeeke as anie other:
<note place="margin">The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors long practiſe of certeine rules ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to this art: as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> yet for that I haue preciſelie prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed theſe rules theſe twentie yeres, I dare be the bolder to ſet downe, in what manner I haue practiſed the ſame, and how much I haue profited thereby, which may ſtand for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation or interpretation of the places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore promiſed, leauing the iudgement and choiſe of euerie one to doo therein as he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. For as I haue no power to binde anie to like of mine, ſo I haue good will to follow o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that will with reaſon in like maner giue me like occaſion to follow them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>How theſe rules haue beene prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed <hi>by this Author.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Cap. 6.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch therefore as ſhall haue deſire to practiſe theſe rules, as I haue doone, let them not forget
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:375:26"/>this, that <hi>Xenophon</hi> and <hi>Gryſon</hi> agree both, that aſſoone as one is mounted on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, he muſt ſit quietlie there a while, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie if he be to be taught. <hi>Xenophon</hi> ſheweth the reaſon why:
<note place="margin">The incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences of ſudden motions procured in a horſſe by the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> for (ſaith he) all ſudden moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons breed perturbations in the mind of an horſſe, and whiles he is in that caſe, he cannot well learne. For he is not aſſured of himſelfe, nor of that which his rider would haue him do, for (as we ſaie) he is not himſelfe that is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in mind. And therefore he willeth, when the horſſe is firſt moued, that it ſhould be doon as ſoftlie and quietlie as one could deuiſe, to what action ſo euer you meane to put him. And ſeeing that <hi>Gryſon</hi> would, that all his doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſhould be doone vpon a ſtaied hand, a iuſt, placed, and ſetled head, with a pleaſant mouth vpon the bit, which he accompteth to be the cheefe point and whole ſubſtance of horſſemanſhip.</p>
            <p>Therefore I haue beene verie preciſe in practiſing the making of his mouth to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and to mainteine him in the perfection thereof, the which if anie will follow, he muſt (after he hath ſitten quietlie a while) firſt cauſe the horſſe to go backe according to the order appointed. For vpon that motion he will
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:375:26"/>bring in his head, and ſettle himſelfe (as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid) in euerie reſpect: and in that order then ſtand ſtill a while, and make much of him: and in that meane while, if he continue not in the ſaid order, then make him go a little backe againe (as before.) But if he continue ſtill in the ſaid good order and forme, then mooue him faire and gentlie forward vpon the pace, with the calues of your legges, keeping your hand ſtaied, ſo as you neither draw it, nor ſlack it, offering your bodie ſomewhat forward withall, and ſo go foorth right in a ſtrait path, betweene two furrowes, ſo farre as <hi>Gryſon</hi> dooth appoint.
<note place="margin">Defaults of diſorder in an horſſe, and howto be remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the rider.</note> If by the waie he make anie diſorder, by thruſting out of his head, or waxe heauie vpon the hand, or leaue champing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bit, the which you muſt note diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, aſſoone as you perceiue it, by and by ſtaie faire and gentlie, and make him go backe as you did before. For in the going backe he will bring himſelfe in his right forme and order, wherein as ſoone as you find him, make much of him, and mooue him forward foorthwith faire and gentlie, and after this maner vſe him ſtill, till he come to the place of ſtop. And as he muſt be vſed thus in going right forward, ſo likewiſe muſt he be vſed in treading of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:375:27"/>rings, firſt gentlie vpon the pace, and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vpon the trot, and laſt of all vpon the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop. And in the practiſing heereof, you muſt verie preciſelie note theſe kinds of ſpeeches: that in making of a horſſe to go backe,
<note place="margin">A tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſtaied, and firme hand requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a horſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire or go backe: and that manie profeſſed riders miſſe the due vſe thereof.</note> it ſhould be doone with a temperate, a ſtaied, and a firme hand. But what the temperate, ſtaied, and firme hand meaneth, and how it is vnderſtood and vſed of the moſt part that take vpon them to profeſſe this art, when they will at the beginning make their horſſes go backe, I know not. But you ſhall ſee them draw the reines with a forced hand, rather than with a temperate hand, whereby they ſo preſſe the horſſes mouth, that they put it cleane out of order, which may be perceiued either by ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or thruſting his toong vpon the bit, to defend himſelfe from the ſame, or els ouer the bit, chopping his head out ſuddenlie, and plucking it in diſdainefullie, ſeeking by moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his head this waie and that waie, to be deliuered of the ſaid preſſing: which be all ſignes of an vntemperate hand, inclining to violence, and contrarie to nature, which to content and pleaſe is the end of the whole art. And therefore one ſhould practiſe this rule in ſuch ſort, as the ſtanders by ſhould ſcarſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:375:27"/>perceiue whether he draweth the reines ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with or no, and that in this manner.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">A forme of practiſing the former rule, and what things are well to be marked.</note> as ſoone as he is ſetled in the ſadle (as aforeſaid) let him not draw the reines of the bridle vnto him, before he haue made them equall, ſo that one be no longer than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And if it be a horſſe, that knoweth not well the bit, then let the bit be as ſlacke as he can, and let him ſettle his left hand, wherein he holdeth the reines with his little finger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene, vnder the pomell of the ſaddle, as neere the withers as he can, ſo as he touch them not, and then with his right hand draw the reines faire and ſoftlie, and equallie togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through his left hand, the which he may neuer remooue, vntill he feele that the horſſe begin to ſtaie vpon the bit: then let him hold the reines there, neither ſlacking them, nor drawing them anie further, vntill he doo looke in what forme his head ſtandeth, the which if it be not in ſuch due forme as before is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, then let him giue him his left hand againe a little, and ſtanding ſo with him a pretie while, let him bring his left hand to his former place againe, whereas he found the horſſe to make his firſt ſtaie vpon the bit, and there if he ſtand without making anie motion either with his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:375:28"/>mouth vpon the bit, or with his head, which if you note well, you ſhall perceiue that he will ſtand therewith (as it were) doubting, or in a mammering, whether he ſhould put it out, or bring it in, as though he were troubled with the palſie, which you ſhall ſcarſe perceiue by the motion: then draw the reines with your right hand, through your left hand ſomewhat more, but let it be ſo little, and in ſuch gentle ſort, as the ſtanders by may ſcarſe perceiue it; for ſo muſt all the motions of the hand be at that time,
<note place="margin">Motions of the riders hand, in ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the reines, &amp;c.</note> if you will make the horſſe know the bit, and ſo keepe it firme and ſtaied there a pretie while: wherevpon if he yeeld anie thing (be it neuer ſo little) vnto your hand, keepe your hand ſtill at one ſtaie, neither ſlacking it, nor drawing it anie further, that he may feele the eaſe gotten by that his yeelding, and vpon his ſo yeelding make much of him. And if with that yeelding the reines fall ſlacke, remooue not your left hand, but draw the reines with your right hand through your left, as you did before, for they may not lie ſlacke vntill he ſtaie againe vpon your hand, wherevnto if he doo yeeld by anie of thoſe motions afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentioned, then make much of him, and ſo after this ſort ſollicite him, vntill you haue
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:375:28"/>brought his head into his due place, that is, that his noſe lie iuſt vnder his forehead, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too much out, nor too much in, but ſo as he may ſee where he may ſet his feete. When you haue brought him to this,
<note place="margin">To make your horſſe offer to go backe, with other acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> if then he beare not light vpon the hand, let his keeper or ſome other ſtrike him faire and gentlie vpon the knees of his forelegs, for that will make him offer to go backe, and in that offering he will a little raiſe and bring in his head, in the which motion the bit will mooue, ſo as both he and you ſhall feele ſome eaſe thereof. But at that inſtant take great heed that you keepe your hand ſo firme, that you neither ſlacke it, nor in anie wiſe drawe it vnto you, to the end that he may feele the eaſe that he found by the ſame motion, the which he will not with his good will loſe againe, and therevpon he will take ſuch pleaſure, as peraduenture he will both ſtir the bit quietlie in his mouth, and go backe withall likewiſe, either of the which motions ought diligentlie to be noted, for they be tokens of the preſent winning of his mouth, the which once woon in this order, you ſhall by continuance thereof bring it to be perfect and iuſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:375:29"/>
            <head>A continuation of the matter <hi>diſcourſed vpon in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> chapter.</head>
            <head>Cap. 7.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt aboue all things you muſt take heed,
<note place="margin">What is to be auoided in teaching a horſſe &amp;c.</note> that in the preſent time of the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of him this, you vexe not, nor trouble him with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other thing, nor that in this dailie exerciſing of him heerevnto, you ſuffer none other to ride him, vntill his mouth be made perfect, leaſt by feeling the diuerſitie of hands before he be aſſured of anie one, he be ſo confuſed with the diuerſitie, as he ſhall neuer be able to attaine to a certeine and ſure conceipt of the riders meaning, and then ſhall he neuer willinglie obey vnto the will and meaning of his rider,
<note place="margin">The end of the whole art of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is, that the horſſe do willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie obey his rider.</note> which is the end of the whole Art. And when by theſe meanes he is brought to know the iuſt ſtaie of his head, and aſſured of the bit, then to mainteine him therein in all his dooings, vntill he may come vnto his full perfection, is firſt to pace him in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:375:29"/>this forme and order in rings that be large for one weeke at the leaſt: and alwaies when you find him out of order, ſtaie him, and make him go backe, as is before mentioned. And when he is in order, ſtaie him not long, but making much of him, keepe your hand firme, and put him faire and gentlie into his pace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; and then if he continue in his good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, with making much of him, moue him qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etlie to go faſter vpon the pace, with giuing him your bodie, and touching him ſoftlie with the calfes of your legs: but neither ſlacke nor drawe your hand to you, for that is the firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that is meant: and haſt him ſo, vntill he fall into a trot of himſelfe, &amp; that he will doo verie light vpon your hand, the which you muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies keep in ſuch temper, as was laſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, vnles by bringing in his head, the reines fall ſlacke, for then they muſt be drawne with the right hand, as you haue heard before.
<note place="margin">What is to be doone to the horſſe when he continueth not light vpon your hand in trot.</note> But if he doo not vpon the trot continue light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your hand, then ſtaie him, and cauſe him to go back, wherby you ſhall bring him in order, and that doon, put him gentlie into his pace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſo bring him into his trot as before. And though you find him in the beginning verie vntoward, yet within an houres exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:375:30"/>of him in this gentle maner, you ſhall find him toward inough, as by proofe you ſhall perceiue.
<note place="margin">Diuers waies to cheriſh your horſſe.</note> And then aſſoone as you ſhall find him ſo, cheriſh him with ſome little tickling, or ſome ſcratching with the end of your rod, or with your fingers vpon the withers, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts in the necke, and trauell him for that time but verie little more, and ſo leaue him, and alight off from him euen there, and let him be lead home by ſome leading reine, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than by the reines of the bridle or head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall (as manie vſe to doo) and at your next riding you ſhall find him better diſpoſed; and by exerciſing of him thus but a fornight toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you ſhall find (by experience) great good hope of your trauell. And when he will in this quiet ſort pace and trot in good order, then may you put him to trot with as much ſpeed as you will haue him, both the rings, or in anie kind of manage.
<note place="margin">When to put your horſſe to the gallop, and what is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in his ſpeedie trot, and in his gallop.</note> But let him not gallop, vntill he be fullie perfect vpon the trot, and in his ſpeedie trot you muſt keepe your ſeate and hand firme, ſo as he may not leeſe his orderlie and comelie forme before preſcribed. But if you will put him to gallop, you muſt doo it out of the trot, as you be taught to put him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the trot, out of the pace, and ſo to keepe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:375:30"/>him in a quiet gallop in the large rings, euen to the ſtop, at the which you muſt not drawe your hand haſtilie to you, but euen with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſwaie of your bodie backe, and your hand togither. Staie your hand there till he come backe a ſtep or twoo, and there ſtaie him, and let him not go forward; and there withall if he doo well, make much of him, and let your hand with your bodie go to their place againe. But if he offer to go forward, then with the like ſwaie ſtaie him, and ſo let him ſtand ſtill a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie while, making much of him, and then alight there, and let him be lead home, or elſe faire and ſoftlie pace him home from thence after you haue ſtaied there with him a good pretie while.</p>
            <p>But now, if you will be aſſured,
<note place="margin">How to be aſſured whether you haue the right vſe and temper of the hand, and that the horſſe be well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the bit.</note> whether you haue the right vſe and temper of the hand, and that the horſe be well aſſured of the bit, pace your horſe ouerthwart the fallow of a new ploughed land that is deepe, and of a light mould, as faſt as you can, ſo that he trot not, halfe an houre togither, and keepe your hand in the firme and temperate ſtaie, as is before preſcribed. If in this time, and in your ſo doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the horſſe keepe his head in his due place, beare light vpon your hand, and take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the bit: you may aſſure your ſelfe that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:375:31"/>you haue then obteined the right knowledge of the vſe of the hand, wherein the cheefe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this Art dooth conſiſt. By this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe alſo,
<note place="margin">To bring a horſſe to a iuſt trot is verie hard.</note> you ſhall bring your horſſe to trot iuſt, which <hi>Gryſon</hi> thinketh to be the hardeſt thing to bring a horſſe vnto, by the meanes of which (ſaith he) the horſſe ſhall come vnto the perfection of all his other iuſt dooings.</p>
            <p>But my purpoſe is not to treate of anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing at this time,
<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this treatiſe.</note> but onelie of the right vſe of the hand, which hitherto hath beene treated of, as concerning the teaching and making of a horſſe. And now we are to treate of the vſe of the hand vpon a horſſe alreadie taught, and fit for the ſeruice, wherein we haue but the vſe of the left hand onelie: for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt ſerue vs for our weapon whatſoeuer it be. But leaſt that ſome may thinke that <hi>Gryſon</hi> and <hi>Xenophon</hi> for the vſe of the hand be of contrarie minds (as it is ſomewhat tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before) I thinke good before I proceed anie further in this, to ſhew mine opinion of their difference.
<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary minds of <hi>Gryſon</hi> &amp; <hi>Xenophon</hi> touching the vſe of the hand, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gryſon</hi> affirmeth conſtantlie, that vpon the horſſes yeelding vnto the hand, wee ſhould giue him no libertie at all, and that in diuers places he affirmeth. And <hi>Xenophon</hi> cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:375:31"/>ſaith; that aſſoone as he bringeth in his head, and boweth in the necke, you ſhould by and by ſlacke and eaſe your hand. His words be theſe; The horſſes mouth may not bee ſo preſſed with the bit, that thereby he be put in deſpaire of libertie, nor yet ſo eaſilie and ſoft that he ſhould contemne the ſame. Note well therefore the proportion of this meaſure: and ſo he goeth on &amp; ſaith; When you haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what preſſed him with the bridle, ſo as he cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his necke in good order, then muſt you by and by eaſe your bridle, &amp; make much of him aſſoone as he ſheweth himſelfe obedient vnto you. And a little after; If the horſſe ſeeme to be well pleaſed with the eaſing of your hand, and taketh a pride (as it were) in raiſing of his neck and creſt, take heed then euen at that preſent, leaſt anie thing doo vex or greeue him; but with gentle dealing he muſt be vſed as he may hope for reſt.
<note place="margin">How the head and necke of a horſſe ſhould be placed.</note> In the beginning of his booke he ſheweth, how he would haue the head and necke ſhould be placed, not riſing out of the breaſt inclining downeward, as it is in a goate or hog; but riſing vpward toward the crowne like a cocke, ſomewhat bending in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, ſo as the eie of the horſſe may ſee his owne feet. This is the ſumme of <hi>Xenophons</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:375:32"/>Now let vs ſee what <hi>Gryſon</hi> ſaith; to the end we may know wherein they agree and diſagree, and whether the ſame be in word or meaning. For the placing of the head, and framing and faſhioning of the necke they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and both they would haue his head ſo placed, as he may ſee where to ſet his feete, and when he ſheweth himſelfe obedient, to be much made of.
<note place="margin">What waie is beſt to make a a horſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand when he dooth well: and how <hi>Xenophon</hi> and <hi>Gryſon</hi> differ in the maner thereof.</note> For the horſſe can no better waie be made to vnderſtand when he dooth well, than by eaſe and reſt, and much making of, wherein he may take ſome pleaſure. But in the manner how he ſhould be made to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this eaſe and much making of, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the diuerſitie. For the one would haue him vnderſtand it by ſlacking the hand, and the other (as it ſeemeth) would not haue him haue anie libertie at all. For (ſaith he) when you haue brought the head of the horſſe in his due place with thoſe ſignes before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, giue him then no libertie at all. But ſtraitwaies he putteth (as it were) a caueat: Let the ſtaiedneſſe be ſuch, that it be not out of his due temperance. For therevpon he will take great pleaſure, champing the bit, and be maruellous light vpon the hand, &amp;c. Now therefore if we conſider <hi>Xenophons</hi> proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:375:32"/>in ſlacking of the hand with <hi>Gryſons</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint and caueat thereto added, we ſhall find that they differ nothing in meaning, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they differ in words.
<note place="margin">The opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> and <hi>Gryſon,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant or different, reconciled.</note> For the ſlacking of the hand on the one ſide, and the ſtraining thereof on the other ſide, ſhould be ſuch as the horſſe might find eaſe, and take pleaſure ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For as there is no pleaſure in ouerſtraining, no more is there in ouerſlacking: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that can find the iuſt meane betwixt theſe two extreames, dooth happen vpon the true meaning of theſe two excellent perſons, which (in mine opinion) differ not in meaning but in word.
<note place="margin">A reaſon drawne from the art of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, for the better explaining of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> As we perceiue in the Art of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, vpon inſtruments with ſtrings, if any one ſtring be ſtrained or ſlacked more than his due meaſure, the pleaſure of the whole muſicke is loſt: euen ſo, the vntuned or vntemperate hand dooth marre the pleſantnes of the horſes mouth; neither can anie with reaſon thinke, that he which would haue the ſtring ſlacked when it is too much ſtrained, neither the other which would haue it ſtrained when it is too ſlacke, that they be contrarie in meaning: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they both would, that the inſtrument ſhould be ſo tuned, as the muſicke might yeeld the pleaſant effect. But ſee (I praie you)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:375:33"/>diligentlie, how nice and warie theſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent perſons be in this moſt skilfull point of Horſſemanſhip, without the true knowledge of which, all the reaſt in compariſon is but vaine.</p>
            <p>You ſee, they deuiſe no hard or ſharpe bits, no pricking muſrolles, or <hi>Cauezzans,</hi> or ſuch other like inſtruments of violence, whereby the ſenſe in continuance is either made dull or dead; but rather how they may delight and pleaſe them as nature and art requireth. But this mine interpretation of this place, and all the reſt which I haue vſed, by ſhewing in what ſort I haue practiſed them, I leaue to the iudgement of others, and now go on with that which was purpoſed, that is, to ſhew the right vſe of the hand vpon horſes that be alreadie made perfect and iuſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>The right vſe of the hand vpon a horſſe <hi>alreadie made perfect and iuſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Cap. 8.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow then,
<note place="margin">What is to be doone when a horſſe is perfected according to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors rules.</note> when a horſſe is thus taught and brought to perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as <hi>Gryſon</hi> ſaith in the 107. page) we ſhall not need to vſe the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:375:33"/>rod or anie other helpe, but to keepe our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, hands, thighes, knees, and legs iuſt in ſuch ſort as I haue told you before, that is which is ſet foorth in his owne booke.
<note place="margin">Mutuall conſent of the horſſe and the horſſeman by what meanes procured.</note> For the horſſe with euerie little token by aide of the bridle, and of the ſpurre will vnderſtand your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and in euerie act that you ſhall doo, he will accompanie you, and you ſhall accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie him in time and meaſure, ſo as to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders it ſhall appeare, that he and you be one bodie, of one mind, and of one will. In this point therefore, firſt there is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, how in the left hand the reines be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and how they are then to be vſed: for therein moſt cheefelie ſtandeth the whole go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement which <hi>Gryſon</hi> likeneth to the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the ſtearne that gouerneth the ſhip: and theſe reines (as he ſheweth in the 109. page, which he willeth to note, beginning at theſe words <hi>Notateche</hi>) muſt alwaies be placed in this maner,
<note place="margin">M. <hi>Blunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiles</hi> rule for the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the reines.</note> which Maiſter <hi>Blundeuile</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred in the tenth chapter of his firſt booke thus: As touching the reines, you muſt hold them in your left hand, ſo as the little ſinger, and ring finger too (if you will) may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be placed betweene the twoo reines, and the thombe cloſe vpon the reines, with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:375:34"/>the brawne thereof turned toward the pomell of the ſaddle, and being thus cloſed togither in your fiſt, <hi>Gryſon</hi> in the 39. page, beginning at <hi>Quando volterete, &amp;c,</hi> ſheweth, how the fiſt muſt then be vſed, when you will turne your horſſe in whatſoeuer kind of manage it be, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner: Doo not (ſaith he) remoue your arme or hand, but keepe it firme and ſtaied right ouer the creſt or mane of the horſſe, and with a little ſigne or token giuen after a certeine manner, by turning your fiſt onelie, make him to know on whatſide you would haue him turne, but yet ſo as your fiſt in anie wiſe keepe the appointed place right ouer the mane, neither remoouing it of the one ſide, nor the other, to the end he may go firme and iuſt. Thus farre <hi>Gryſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maiſter <hi>Claudio Corte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the fiſt M. <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio Corte</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of the rider, when he ſhould turne his horſſe on anie fide.</note> in the ſecond booke of his <hi>Cauallarizzo,</hi> as he intituleth it, for the placing of the hand and the reines, agreeth fullie with <hi>Gryſon,</hi> but is ſomewhat more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in declaring the maner of the motion of the fiſt, when one ſhuld turne him of anie ſide. For (ſaith he) if you will turne him on the right hand, then bow your fiſt, ſo as your thombe maie turne downe toward the mane of the horſſe, as therby you may ſee the full backe of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:375:34"/>your hand, with your little finger vppermoſt. And when you will turne him on the left hand, then contrariwiſe turne your fiſt ſo, as the thombe may go backe from you toward the head of the horſſe, and that you may ſee all your fingers in the inſide of your fiſt, ſo that your little finger and ring finger may appeere more fullie vnto you than your thombe, but yet no more nor leſſe than need ſhall require; but ſo as your hand remooue verie little from the appointed place, either of the one ſide of the necke or the other, and that according to euerie mans skill that vſeth it. But I know well (ſaith he) that verie few haue the true vſe of it. And heere doubting (as it ſeemeth) whether his meaning ſhould be vnderſtood in this point, addeth;
<note place="margin">M. <hi>Claudio Corte</hi> doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning will be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood but of a few.</note> And peraduenture there be few that vnderſtand me (ſaith he) though I haue ſet it downe verie plaine. And ſo ſurelie to doubt he had great reaſon. For truelie I feare that to the moſt part this which hath hitherto beene ſaid of either of them, will ſeeme but a riddle, and therefore had need of further explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>There is no doubt, but that theſe excellent perſons vnderſtood ſome grounded reaſon of this precept, if it had pleaſed them as well to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:375:35"/>haue ſet downe the reaſon as the rule: for that being knowne, the rule will eaſilie be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. Let vs endeuor our ſelues therefore to ſeeke it out.
<note place="margin">The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the verie forme of <hi>Gryſons</hi> and <hi>Claudios</hi> rule tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the turning of the fiſt, &amp;c.</note> What mine opinion is thereof, and vpon the which I reſt, vntill I haue others to perſwade me otherwiſe, is this, which I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the verie forme of the ſaid rule, and that is of the placing of the hand and reines, and of the motion of the fiſt, as you haue read before, as the hand not to remooue from the creſt of the horſſe, the little finger and the ring finger (if your will) be placed betweene the reines, &amp;c. <hi>Gryſon</hi> biddeth vs turne our fiſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a certeine maner, but ſheweth not how. <hi>Claudio</hi> goeth further, and ſheweth how one ſhould turne his fiſt, but no cauſe whie hee ſhould ſo turne it: and therefore (in mine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) to make it plaine, this I adde vnto it, and would haue all men note, that when I find the fingers thus placed betweene the reines, and find alſo that the left reine lieth cloſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in the inſide of the fingers, and the right reine vpon the outſide of thoſe fingers, this being well noted, you ſhall ſtraight ſee the reaſon, whie or to what end that motion of the fiſt that <hi>Claudio</hi> dooth ſhew, tendeth vnto. For (ſaith he) when you will turne the horſſe on the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:375:35"/>right hand, turne your fiſt ſo as your thombe may go downeward to the horſſes mane, that your little finger may riſe vp, on the outſide of the which the right reine lieth, and by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that motion is raiſed vp, and the left falleth,
<note place="margin">By what accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſignes the horſſe knoweth when his rider would haue him turne on the right ſide and when on the left.</note> and therewith the horſſe feeleth the right reine ſtraighted, and the left ſlacked, which he knoweth by cuſtome to be the ſigne to haue him turne on the right ſide. And ſo likewiſe when you would haue him turne on the left hand, he turneth his fiſt ſo, that his thombe goeth backe toward the necke of the horſſe, as he may ſee all his fingers in the inſide of his hand. By the which motion he raiſeth the left reine, which is in the inſide of his hand, and the right alſo falleth, with the which the horſſe feeling himſelfe neuer ſo little ſtreined on the left ſide, knoweth by that ſigne, that he ſhould turne on the left ſide.</p>
            <p>Now whether that this be the forme and maner of turning of the hand that <hi>Gryſon</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, I know not, but in effect certeinelie they meane all one, as I gather by <hi>Gryſon</hi> in the 69. page, where he teacheth how one ſhould cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect a horſſe with the bit, that holdeth his necke awrie, beginning thus, <hi>Oude ſimilmente, &amp;c.</hi> If (ſaith <hi>Gryſon</hi>) he hold it awrie on the left ſide,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:375:36"/>hold your bridle in the woonted place, that is right ouer the creſt, and take the right reine vp with the forefinger of the bridle hand, the which reine you ſhall hold betweene the ſaid finger and your thombe, and if you ſee cauſe, you may ioine your middle finger therewith alſo. But if it be too plieng on the right ſide, and ſtiffe on the left, then hold not onelie the little finger in his due place, betweene both the reines, but alſo the ring finger and middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt too, ſo as on what ſide ſoeuer his fault be, by this meanes you ſhall force him by little and little, to yeeld vnto that part of the necke that is ſtiffe. What he meaneth by vſing the reines in this maner, for the correction of this fault, euerie child may conceiue the reaſon. And herevpon I gather,
<note place="margin">How to ſignifie on which ſide the rider would haue his horſſe to turne.</note> that in what maner ſo euer he mooueth his hand, to ſignifie on which ſide he would haue the horſſe to turne, it is by ſtaieng the reine on that ſide, and ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it on the other, as I haue ſhewed before. And therefore (for mine owne part) I vſe in practiſing therof, to take part with them both, ſo farre foorth as I find it moſt handſome for my hand, as thus. When I turne him on the left hand, I vſe <hi>Claudio</hi> his motion, to bow my fiſt ſo as my thombe may go backward toward
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:375:36"/>the horſſes head, whereby I raiſe the left reine that lieth in the inſide of my little finger, by raiſing that part of my hand wherein that reine lieth: and when I turne him on the right ſide, then I take vp the right reine with my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finger (as <hi>Gryſon</hi> teacheth in the place before recited, though it perteine not properlie to this) and leaue the turning of my fiſt as <hi>Claudio</hi> teacheth with my thombe downe, and my lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle finger vppermoſt, on the outſide whereof the right reine lieth, which I find oftentimes to ſlip from the place, but ſo I am ſure the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waie, if I take it with my forefinger or middle finger it cannot, and ſo vnto me I find it more handſome. But yet I leaue both theſe or anie other to euerie perſon to vſe, as he findeth it moſt fitteſt for him: ſo that they ſwarue not from theſe naturall grounds, that the hand keepe his appointed place, and that the motion therof be ſuch, as when one dooth turne a horſſe on anie ſide, he ſhould ſtaie or ſtraine him with the reine on that ſide.</p>
            <p>And the lacke of the knowledge in this point is the cauſe that maketh our horſſes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the tilt oftentimes:
<note place="margin">The cauſe whi horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes doo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes forſake the tilt.</note> for it is well neere a common thing, that when a horſſe dooth paſſe along the tilt, to ſee him carie his head rather
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:375:37"/>from, than toward the ſame. The reaſon is, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that paſſeth him, draweth his bridle hand toward the tilt, thinking therby to cauſe the horſſe to yeeld his head and bodie toward the ſame, and dooth not perceiue, how by that motion of the hand, hee ſtreineth the right reine which is on the right ſide of the horſſe, that is from the tilt, and ſlacketh the left reine next vnto the tilt, ſo as the horſſe cannot for his life keepe his head towards the ſame. And thus haue I made this matter as plaine as my skill or wit will ſerue, and as I haue conceiued it in mine opinion, the which I leaue to the iudgement of others. And heerewithall yet one may ſee now how plaine it is, when the reaſon is added to the rule.
<note place="margin">What the Author once pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the bookes of <hi>Gryſon</hi> and <hi>Xenophon</hi> treating of the Art of riding.</note> And in this maner was I once minded to haue gone through the whole booke of <hi>Gryſon</hi> with verie ſhort notes, and to haue added thervnto <hi>Xenophons</hi> booke of the Art of riding. But now I meane to ſtaie, and expect what will be the iudgement of this my firſt labour, and how it will be allowed among the skilfull ſort of them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe this Art, to whoſe reaſonable correction &amp; fauourable inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation this worke dooth offer it ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:375:37"/>
            <head>¶ The commodities that may be <hi>found by the vſing of the hand in this</hi> maner, in practiſing of <hi>Gryſon</hi> his rules <hi>and his order of teaching,</hi> be theſe.</head>
            <head type="sub">Cap. 9.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt,
<note place="margin">Particular commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be attained by practiſing the rules and order ſet downe by <hi>Gryſon.</hi>
               </note> you ſhall neuer put your horſſe in danger of winde and limme, or other deformitie of his bodie: in which if nature hath made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie default, it may greatlie be helped thereby.</p>
            <p>Next, your horſſe ſhall neuer put your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in perill by rearing or running awaie, if you haue the ſaid true vſe of the hand.</p>
            <p>Againe, he ſhall neuer greeue his rider with heauie bearing vpon his hand: but ſhall beare light, reine well, and keepe his head ſteddie, and haue a perfect mouth, taking pleaſure vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bit, with a cheerefull pace vnder him, vnleſſe he be too too dull of nature.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, to bring theſe things to paſſe,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:375:38"/>you ſhall not need to beſtow your monie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Cauezzans,</hi> chaines, muſrolles, or martin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales, or anie ſuch inſtruments, but of a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non bit onelie with falſe reines, vntill he come to ſome towardnes, and then to bit him, as ye ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
            <p>For theſe things aforeſaid were deuiſed by men of art,
<note place="margin">To what end, <hi>Cauez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> chains, muſrolles, &amp;c. were deuiſed.</note> not for their owne vſe, but for to traine vp yoong beginners, and to bring them thereby to the knowledge of the hand, their ſeate, and when, and how they ſhould aid an horſſe, cheriſh and correct him before they would truſt them to ride him with the bit one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. And ſo <hi>Gryſon</hi> affirmeth, <hi>Che il caualiero fondato in buona doctrina ſenza di cio lo togliera non ſolo di queſto ma d'ogn' altro vitio,</hi> that is, That the rider grounded in the right order of teaching without it (meaning the <hi>Cauezzan,</hi> or ſuch like inſtruments) ſhall take awaie not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie this fault (treating in that place of the fault which the horſſe committeth when he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his head awrie) from him, but alſo euerie other whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Finallie, by this you ſhall know, to whom you may commit your horſſe ſafelie and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredlie to be taught, thereby to haue him in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:375:38"/>all his aſſaies to ſerue your turne, and of whom you may be aſſured to find the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For he that hath an horſſe, which by nature beareth heauie vpon the hand (whereof there be but few if there be anie at all) or be brought thereto for lacke of skill in the rider (of which there be too manie) and ſuffreth ſuch an horſſe to go out of his hand vnrecouered of the ſaid fault, ſo as the horſſe doo not all his actions vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a light and ſtaied hand, with pleaſure and comelines, and that with a cannon bit onelie (as is aforeſaid) he is not to be truſted with a horſſe of anie value.
<note place="margin">Note with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge of what point in the Art of riding all the reſt in compariſon is but vaine.</note> For without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this point of riding, all the reſt in compariſon is but vaine. Neither ſhall anie man euer be able without it to bring a horſſe to that luſtines of courage, and comelineſſe of ſhape, that <hi>Xenophon</hi> requireth in all his doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which he himſelfe dooth repreſent and expreſſe, when he would appeare moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull. But he that can (ſaith he) bring that to paſſe, ſhall cauſe not onelie the rider, but alſo the horſſe to take great pleaſure in the riding, ſo as therein he ſhall appeare verie noble, terrible, and beautifull to behold; yea, and ſo delight the eies of the beholders, with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:375:39"/>thereat, that neither yoong nor old will be willing to depart ſo long as he is a riding. Thus ſaith <hi>Xenophon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth this treatiſe with <hi>Gryſon.</hi>
               </note> Therefore with the laſt ſentence of <hi>Gryſons</hi> booke, I conclude thus: <hi>Queſta e quell'arte laqual ſi ſegne da molti, &amp; e tanta la difficolta, che vn ſolo ſara colui che al fui compita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente arriuera al ſuo vero ſegno.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:375:39"/>
            <head>¶ This diſcourſe following of the <hi>Chaine or Cauezzan, and likewiſe of the</hi> Trench &amp; Martingale, is not the Authors worke, <hi>but the experience of another Gentleman verie skilfull and long</hi> practiſed in the ſame Art, which he hath briefelie written at the <hi>request of his inward freend.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He chaine or <hi>Cauez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How the <hi>Cauezzan</hi> is to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the riders hands.</note> when a horſſe is come to were a cannon, would be caried in both hands in ſuch ſort, as the rider may alwaies haue power to commaund his horſſe. And therefore you are to carie the chaine (at the firſt) lower than the pomell of the ſaddle, euen, and ſomewhat ſhort: for ſo ſhall you be euer readie to helpe your horſſe vpon anie occaſion. But beware, that you doo not hale, or hang vpon the chaine continuallie with a hard and cruell hand, for thereby you may make your horſſe ſo dull thereof, as he will not care for it. Wherefore (in mine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) to make a horſſe vnderſtand and know the chaine, and to be light thereof, it were not amiſſe, to trot him out in ſome faire peece of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:375:40"/>ground, where you may haue roome inough to trot and ſtop at your will, &amp; there trot your horſſe right out, a good long carrires length, and in his trot, carie the reines of the chaine in your hands (as aforeſaid) euer regarding your horſſes head, that he carie the ſame iuſt, and in a good place, not more of the oneſide than of the other, and high enough at the firſt, though he carie his noſe out. But in anie wiſe doo not ſuffer him to ſinke with his head, or carie it downewards:
<note place="margin">A fowle fault in the horſſe to ſinke with his head, &amp;c: and no leſſe in the rider to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it.</note> for beſides that it is a fowle fault in the horſſe to doo it, it is no leſſe in the rider to ſuffer it, if ſmall and gentle helpes and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections may reforme it: for (at the firſt) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame corrections are not (in anie wiſe) to be vſed, for they will doo more harme than good.</p>
            <p>Therefore, let your hand vpon the reine of the chaine be euer readie, as you be trotting your horſſe to the place of ſtop, to giue him a little nippe or warning patientlie, and at the ſame inſtant, put him forwards with your legs or voice gentlie, ſhaking your rod withall, to the end he may go franklie vnder you, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the reine of the chaine ſtill at one ſtaie, vnles you find in your diſcretion, he deſerue to haue ſome libertie, and ſo ſuffer him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es to go forwards at his owne eaſe: but
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:375:40"/>take heede, that the gripes and pinches, which you giue your horſſe with the chaine, make him not fearfull to go forwards, or to offer to ſtop, before you come to the place where you intend to haue him ſtop. Wherefore as you ſhall keepe your chaine in one place, and at one ſtaie for a conuenient time (as aforeſaid) vntill he waxe humble therof, that by his yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he maie winne his owne eaſe, and keepe his head where you would haue it: ſo muſt you carie it with ſo temperate a hand, as you maie rather ſeeme to threaten with the chaine, than to puniſh, that the horſſe be not made hard therof, neither ſo ſlacke, as he maie contemne, or not care for the ſame.</p>
            <p>For auoiding whereof,
<note place="margin">A remedie for auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the former fault.</note> you muſt euer take heede, to keepe him ſenſible vpon the chaine, and light withall, ſo as by your diſcreete vſing thereof, he maie know and vnderſtand your meaning, which through your diligence he will doo in ſhort time, if in trotting him, you obſerue the maner aforeſaid: and comming to the place of ſtop, pull in the reines of the chaine and bridle, but not cruellie, nor vpon the ſudden, but by a little forewarning of him, and preſentlie with a more force, make his ſtop good, by pulling in your hands, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:375:41"/>keeping them at one ſtaie, putting forwards your legges a little, and bearing your bodie ſomewhat backward, vntill he hath made his ſtop (which would not be ſhort) and, after a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle pawſe or ſtaie, retired therevpon with obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience (if there be cauſe to retire him) which when you perceiue, keepe your left hand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bridle ſteddie, and make much of him with your right hand, wherein you carie the chaine, &amp; ſo pace him after his ſtop, in a large compaſſe at the firſt, once or twice about, vpon the right hand, and ſo back againe gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, to the place from whence you came, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping your hand vpon the chaine ſteddie, and then trot him to the place of ſtop, in the ſame maner as you did before (for it is good to vſe him for a time to one place of ſtop) ſtill ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an eie to his head, that he carie it in the ſame place that you would haue him: which you ſhall make him doo, by keeping your hand ſhort vpon the chaine, &amp; yet light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, ſo as he looke for ſmart, if he offer to carie his head otherwiſe than you would haue him.</p>
            <p>Alſo,
<note place="margin">What is to be done if the horſſe in trotting carrie not his bodie ſtreight.</note> if your horſſe carrie not his bodie ſtreight in his trotting, but more on the one ſide, than on the other: then obſerue <hi>Gryſons</hi> rule, ſet downe in the fourth chapter of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:375:41"/>booke of the Art of riding, where he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, that if your horſſe ſtop wrong, you make him go two or three yardes further in the ſame path, and there ſtop him, holding the reine of the chaine ſtreighter on that ſide, whereon he moſt forceth your hand, than on the other.
<note place="margin">What is to be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon <hi>Gryſons</hi> words.</note> So we may gather by this, that <hi>Gryſon</hi> would wiſh (at the firſt) we ſhould forbeare to reforme our horſſe, either with heele or rod, when he ſtoppeth awrie, and help him with the chaine in this maner, as for example: If your horſſe in his trotting, will not go ſtraight, but carie his head towards the left ſide, and his buttockes towards the right, then by pulling the reine of the chaine on the right ſide, you ſhall make him yeeld his buttockes the contrarie waie, and go ſtreight, if you carie ſuch a temperate hand vpon the chaine, as the horſſe maie be made obedient thereto with a freſh and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble feeling thereof. And ſeeing that you muſt vſe the chaine for the making of your horſſe iuſt both of head &amp; bodie, you ought to haue this conſideration, that your horſſe with great extremitie be not (in anie wiſe) made hard or dull thereof, as is aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Wherfore it were good ſometimes to carie your horſſe vpon the cannon onelie, and eaſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:375:42"/>him vpon the chaine, taking heede of giuing him too much libertie either of chaine or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, other than by his humilitie and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he ſhall get of himſelfe, for you ſhall ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome giue a horſſe anie libertie, but he will ſeeke more.</p>
            <p>Therfore as you haue conſideration of the chaine,
<note place="margin">The nature and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a horſſe is diſcreetlie to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of the rider: note the horſſes of <hi>Sardinia</hi> &amp; <hi>Corſica.</hi>
               </note> ſo muſt you be well aduiſed of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and diſpoſition of your horſſe. For <hi>Gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſaith, that the horſſes of <hi>Sardinia</hi> and <hi>Corſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> are of a fierce and hote chollerike com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, and therefore thoſe horſſes and ſuch like, would be diſcretlie and patientlie ridden; as a horſſe of a dull and ſlow mettall would be franklie ridden with good life and ſpirit: and to ſuch a horſſe (as is firie) there would be litle correction vſed either with ſpurre or rod. For I hold it better, that the rider by his diſcreete and skilfull foreſight, ſhould keepe his horſſe from errour, than correct him when he hath made a fault. For all corrections are vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to a horſſe, yet ſometime to be vſed: but then the rider muſt haue a iudgement to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, whence the cauſe of his error procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; whether it commeth of the malice and euill diſpoſition of the horſſe, or for that he knoweth not the riders mind, or (at his firſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:375:42"/>breaking) hath beene euill taught and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, with ſuch other like.</p>
            <p>And hauing reſpect to theſe things, you may the better vſe your diſcretion, ſo you take time, with a moderate patience:
<note place="margin">Follie of ignorant riders in correcting their horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> I ſaie a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate patience, bicauſe I haue ſeene ſome horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ridden without all order, ſo long, and with ſuch extremitie of ſpurs and rod, and for want of breath togither, that they haue committed fowle faults; for which faults they haue (euen at that preſent) by the rider been cruellie tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented. Which is none other thing, than to ride a horſſe without diſcretion, and after beat him without reaſon. So, he that findeth faults in his horſſe, and thinketh to reforme him at once by the violence of his correction, dooth none other, than make one fault to be yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: where, if he would vſe patience, take time, and doo it by little and little, he ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme more in one weeke, than otherwiſe in a moneth.</p>
            <p>So, mine opinion is, that our firſt care ought to be, that it be well, iuſt, and in good order that we doo: and afterwards to trauell, that it be franklie, nimblie, and with good ſpirit and courage, both in the man and horſſe, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they ſhall doo. And it ſhall not be amiſſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:375:43"/>(by the waie) to aduiſe you,
<note place="margin">Note, as touching a horſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie light of the hand, &amp; be iuſt and ſteddie of head and bodie, &amp;c.</note> that before your horſſe carie light of the hand, and be iuſt and ſteddie of head and bodie, both in his trot and gallop, and in all his other doings, ſo as he be both readie on the ground, and ſeruiceable, you doo not once put him to anie thing aboue the ground. For when he is made firme and iuſt vpon the ground, you ſhall not ſo ſoone proffer him anie thing aboue the ground, but he will verie aptlie, and readilie learne the fame; aduiſing you likewiſe, vnleſſe you haue manie horſſes, and of them find ſome one (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the reſt) that is light and nimble, and apt for ſuch exerciſe aboue the ground, that you ſhould neuer put your horſſe to anie other dooings than on the ground (as is before mentioned) for manie reſpects: which by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience you ſhall find verie profitable, and were here ſuperfluous to trouble you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: bicauſe (in truth) in this diſcourſe, I haue but onlie ſought to giue you a taſt of my owne experience therein, to ſatisfie his requeſt, who maie command me. Wiſhing, that either time had ſerued me, to haue written more amplie thereof, or that ſome other, more able than my ſelfe, may take encouragement hereby, to ſet it foorth hereafter more exactlie.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:375:43"/>
            <p> The trench and martingale are not alwaies to be vſed, nor yet with euerie horſſe,
<note place="margin">When, how, in what ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and with what horſſes the trench and martingale are to be vſed.</note> but for reformation of ſome fault or vice, that either by nature, or otherwiſe by euill cuſtome is growne in him, as principallie, if he be hard of the chaine and cannon, and humble not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to your hand in his ſtop, as you would haue him. Then put on the trench and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale, which (at the firſt) ſhould not be buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led too ſhort in anie wiſe, neither would the trench be vſed with anie extremitie or cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but at the firſt, for ſix or ſeuen daies your horſſe vſed verie courteouſlie therwith, vntill he be well acquainted with the ſame: and then according to your owne diſcretion, and as your horſſes diſobedience ſhall moue you, vſe the ſame more or leſſe in his ordinarie leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And when thoſe faults be reformed, for which you did vſe the trench and martingale, and your horſſe brought to ſuch perfection therewith, as you maie thinke he is made obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, trie him againe with the chaine and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non temperatelie and diſcreetlie. And then if you find him inclined or diſpoſed to the ſame fault ſtill, for which you vſed the trench and martingale, leaue off onlie the chaine againe, and vſe this helpe: Put a muſroll vpon your
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:375:44"/>horſſe, and buckle the ſame as you ſee cauſe, not too ſtreight, but ſo as the horſſe maie haue libertie to plaie on the cannon, and put a paire of falſe reines to the cannon, and ſo ride him, vnleſſe you doo ſee your horſſe diſpoſed to be vnſteddie with his head: for which fault, you maie then buckle a martingale to the muſroll, to keepe him ſteddie, taking heed you buckle it not too ſhort, and exerciſe him diligentlie in his ordinarie leſſons in that ſort; which by your good and diſcreete handling will ſerue to as good purpoſe for a time, as if you did vſe anie of the other before mentioned, carieng the falſe reines in both your hands, to the end you maie let him take pleaſure vpon the cannon: and ſometimes (as occaſion ſhall ſerue) carie him on the ordinarie reines, and other ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times on the falſe reines: and all is but to the end to make him go light of your hand, and take pleaſure of the cannon.
<note place="margin">A chiefe &amp; principall point of horſſeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> For it is a chiefe &amp; principall point of horſſemanſhip to make your horſſe alwaies carie light on the hand.</p>
            <p>Alſo on the other ſide, when you vſe the trench and martingale, if your horſſe be made too humble or ſlacke vpon your hand (as ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times horſſes wilbe with the ſharpneſſe and crueltie of the trench and hardneſſe of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:375:44"/>muſroll) ſo as you cannot make him firme to your hand, you maie put on a ſmooth trench, and more gentle muſroll, and embolden him therewith, making him go forwards with all gentleneſſe vpon the trench:
<note place="margin">A caueat for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding of extremitie in corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting a horſſe.</note> but beware that in your exerciſing of him you vſe no extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with your rod or ſpurres; for it will rather put furie into him than embolden him. Of which fault though I often admoniſh you in this diſcourſe, let it not ſeeme ſtrange: for (in mine opinion) that Horſſeman which neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to vſe temperance, and to miniſter his correction with iudgement and patience, or omitteth likewiſe to cherriſh his horſſe vpon his weldoing, ſhall marre more horſſes, than he ſhall make readie or ſeruiceable.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
